<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Revelation unrevealed concerning the thousand-yeares reigne of the saints with Christ upon earth. Laying forth the weak grounds, and strange consequences of that plausible, and too-much received opinion. By an unfained lover of truth, peace, order, and just moderation.</title>
            <author>Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 121 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86972</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862668</idno>
  <idno type="VID">114837</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240952762</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1346_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202342</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862668</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99862668e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86972)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114837)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 178:E1346[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Revelation unrevealed concerning the thousand-yeares reigne of the saints with Christ upon earth. Laying forth the weak grounds, and strange consequences of that plausible, and too-much received opinion. By an unfained lover of truth, peace, order, and just moderation.</title>
                  <author>Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 168, 173-234, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.L. for John Bisse, and are to be sold at the Bell in S. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An unfained lover = Joseph Hall.</note>
                  <note>In part a reply to: Archer, John.  The personall raigne of Christ upon earth.</note>
                  <note>[4] p. at end = 1 blank leaf and errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Text continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 17 1649"; the 0 in the date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Archer, John, 17th cent. --  Personall raigne of Christ upon earth.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Jesus Christ --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation --  Criticism, interpretation, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114837:1"/>
            <p>THE REVELATION UNREVEALED.</p>
            <p>Concerning The Thousand-Yeares Reigne of the Saints with CHRIST <hi>upon Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laying forth the weak Grounds, and strange Consequences of that plausible, and too-much received <hi>Opinion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By an unfained Lover of <hi>Truth, Peace, Order,</hi> and just <hi>Moderation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. L.</hi> for <hi>John Bisse,</hi> and are to be sold at the Bell in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:114837:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114837:2"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Preface: shewing the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Revelation, the true im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of the point controversed; and the intention of the Author, pag. 1</item>
               <item n="1">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. That this one difficult place of the Revelation alone expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the thousand years raigne, p. 13</item>
               <item n="2">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. The Prophesie of <hi>Daniel</hi> improperly alledged to this purpose, p. 19</item>
               <item n="3">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. The most urgent passage of the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> cleared, p. 24</item>
               <item n="4">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. These pretended doctrines cannot be grounded upon <hi>Daniel</hi> by way of Type or Analogie
<list>
                     <item>Inquiry, since the words are single, whether the sense be clear, p. 39</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item n="5">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. The divers constructions of the thousand years of Satans shut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up, p. 43</item>
               <item n="6">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. The divers constructions of the thousand years raigne of the Saints, p. 50</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:114837:3"/>
               <item n="7">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. The histories of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Chiliasts briefly reported, p. 65</item>
               <item n="8">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. The summary relation of the doctrine of our brethren the late Millenarians, p. 71
<list>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Archers</hi> Tractate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridged concerning Christs Kingdome and Comming, p. 73</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item n="9">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 9. Mr. <hi>Archers</hi> opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Christs withdrawing to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven again, and the government de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the Saints with their prive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, p. 82</item>
               <item n="10">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 10. The latter part of Christs Kingdome set forth by Mr. <hi>Archer,</hi> both in the occasion, and time of it, p. 89</item>
               <item n="11">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 11. That strain of errour, which runs through the whole dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of Mr. <hi>Archer,</hi> and is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ground of this mis-opinion, p. 100</item>
               <item n="12">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 12. The 1 Paradoxe of Mille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narisme. A Mona chical state of Christ Kingdome in a visible and worldly manner, p. 109
<list>
                     <item>2 Paradoxe; The change of all worldly customes, and putting down all kingly power, p. 113</item>
                     <item>3 Paradoxe; A double judgement, p. 114</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:114837:3"/>
               <item n="13">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. 4 Paradoxe; A threefold comming of Christ, p. 116
<list>
                     <item>5 Paradoxe; A double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection, p. 118</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item n="14">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 14. 6 Paradoxe; A threefold Ascension of Christ into heaven, p. 121</item>
               <item n="15">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 15. 7 Paradoxe; The totall reduction of the ten lost tribes of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, p. 125</item>
               <item n="16">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 16. 8 Paradoxe; The Saints in their immortall and glorious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition medling with these earthly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of government, p. 131</item>
               <item n="17">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 17. 9 Paradoxe; The living Saints mortall, and yet sin-less, p. 133</item>
               <item n="18">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 18. 10 Paradoxe; The ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of all temporal blessings, of riches, long life, &amp;c. without any afflictions under this Monarchie of Christ, p. 139</item>
               <item n="19">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 19. 11 Paradoxe; That so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thousands of immortall and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Saints raigning, the wicked Slaves and Tributaries should be able to raise war against them, p. 144</item>
               <item n="20">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 20. 12 Paradoxe; That the day of judgement should hold a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand years, p. 148</item>
               <item n="21">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 21. 13. Paradoxe: A new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of a double Hell, and the place thereof, p. 154</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:114837:4"/>
               <item n="22">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 22. Strange and improbable Consequents which follow upon this opinion and discourse, p. 157
<list>
                     <item>Conseq. 1 That in the Lords prayer we sue for this Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, which yet was hitherto unheard of, p. 159.</item>
                     <item>Conseq. 2. That Christ in his second comming to judge the earth, should yet leave many wicked men alive, p. 160</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item n="23">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 23. Conseq. 3 That Christ who hath all power should descend from heaven to depute new Governours for his Church, and then withdraw, p. 162</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 24. Conseq. 4 The strange composition of this imagined govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, p. 164
<list>
                     <item>Conseq. 5 All Saints, and yet faith hardly to be found upon earth, at our Saviours comming, p. 165</item>
                     <item>Conseq. 6 If the Apostles shall sway that Monarchie, how doth it stand with the words of Christ? <hi>It shall not be so with you,</hi> p. 166</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item n="25">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 25. Conseq. 7. A disadvantage to the souls of Saints glorified to be fetcht down from heaven to continue 1000 years on earth, <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:114837:4"/>
               <item n="26">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 26. Conseq. 8 Children of the Saints conceived and born in sin, yet true Saints, p. 183</item>
               <item n="27">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 27. Conseq. 9. No use of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, yet prayers heard, p. 186
<list>
                     <item>Conseq. 10 Heaven dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peopled of all it's ancient inhabitants for 2000 years, p. 186</item>
                     <item>Conseq. 11 The souls of Saints to be in so different and une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall condition, p. 187</item>
                     <item>Conseq. 12 That Christ should bring his Saints with him, and yet they on earth before him, p. 188</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item n="28">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 28. The opinion of the first Resurrection to be of Martyrs onely confuted, p. 188</item>
               <item n="29">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 29. <hi>Alstedius</hi> his evasion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the single expression of this Millenary reign, refelled, p. 198</item>
               <item n="30">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 30. No necessity from the Text of admitting this strange Tenet of the reign contended for, p. 201</item>
               <item n="31">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 31. The safe and allowed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of the text insisted on, p. 204</item>
               <item n="32">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 32. An exhortation to stick fast to our old received principles, 209
<list>
                     <item>1 And first, not to believe any Kingdome of Christ but either spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, or heavenly, p. 210</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:114837:5"/>
               <item n="33">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 33. 2 Not to think of any ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute freedome from sin, or afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here below, p. 214</item>
               <item n="34">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 34. 3 Not to expect any other comming of Christ, but that one to his finall judgement, p. 219</item>
               <item n="35">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 35. 4 Not to put the day of the last judgement far from us, nor yet punctually to determine the time of it, p. 223</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 21. 1649/50.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have perused this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemicall discourse against the Tenets of the Millena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and find it to be so lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and judicious, and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with such sweet sobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and gall-less moderation, that I approve it very well worthy the Printing and publishing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Downame.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114837:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F there bee any deeps in Divine Scripture where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Elephant may swim,
<note place="margin">The diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of the Revelation</note>
               <note place="margin">Arias Mō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus <hi>in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary upon the Revelatiō, ridiculous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prets the severall Prophesies by abstracts, as</hi> Terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stris indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stria paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica rusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citas, &amp;c.</note> they are surely to be found in the Book of the <hi>Revelation;</hi> wherein ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great wits have both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised and lost themselves. <hi>Arias Montanus,</hi> that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Spaniard, whose la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours are famous for that noble Edition of the whole Sacred Volume of GOD, when he comes to illustrate
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114837:6"/>the <hi>Revelation,</hi> with his Commentary shames him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe with his improbable glosses, &amp; by his ridiculous abstracts, moves both the wonder, and pitty of the judicious of either Religion, <hi>Castellio,</hi> whose elegant and painfull version of both Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staments, hath wont to pass with the learned for an use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Paraphrase, when hee comes to this Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cujus vix millessimā partem in telligo. Castell. Annotat. in Apocal.</note> is not ashamed to passe a <hi>non intelligo</hi> upon it. Master <hi>Junius,</hi> though given to this last Age for a great light to the holy Text, yet professes himself in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of these mysteries to be in the dark:
<note place="margin">Mysteria valdè ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scura. Jun. Praefat.</note> and no marvell, when <hi>Deodati</hi> grants that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114837:6"/>there are some parts of this Book still reserved under Gods secret Seal;
<note place="margin">Deodati <hi>Argument of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation.</hi>
               </note> the expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation whereof is utterly uncertain.
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews.</hi> B. <hi>Winch.</hi>
               </note> And amongst our selves here at home, one whom no man will envie the reputation of one of the greatest Clerks in his Age; when a plaine man came se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously to him, and asked his opinion concerning an obscure passage in that Book, answered, <hi>My friend, I am not comne so far.</hi> Yet I know not how it comes to passe, such is the nature of our in-bred curiosity, that there is no Booke of the whole Scripture, wherein men are so apt to spend both their time and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114837:7"/>Like as every man is apt to try his strength in lifting at an over-heavie weight; and to offer at the string of that Bow, which is much too strong for him to draw. Whereupon have issued those strange obtorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of some particular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesies to private interests: M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Brightman,</hi> a learned &amp; godly Divine, thinks to find not <hi>England</hi> only, but <hi>Cocill,</hi> and <hi>Walsingham</hi> there; A Belgick Doctor in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod of <hi>Dort</hi> thought to find <hi>Grave Maurice</hi> there; <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annes Brocardus</hi> thinks to finde <hi>Venice</hi> there; and a grave Divine (whose name I will spare) was so confident to finde the <hi>Palatinate</hi> there,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114837:7"/>both in the losse and recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it, as that he would needs present his thoughts to the judicious eys of King JAMES himselfe, with small thanks for his labour; neither wanted there some that made full account to finde the late Victorious <hi>Gustavus Adolphus</hi> therein plainly designed; as if the Blessed Apostle, now in his <hi>Pathmos,</hi> over-looking all the vast Continent betwixt us, should have had his thoughts taken up with our petty Occurrences in this other side of the World. What should I tell how many both of our own and Forreign Divines have baf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and shamed themselves
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114837:8"/>in pre-defining out of their mis-taken constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the utmost period of the World, and have confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly set God a day for his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall judgement.</p>
            <p>As for this place which we have in hand,
<note place="margin">The true importance of the point con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversed.</note> how rocky and shelvy it is, appears too well in those ribs of split<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Vessels, which lye still scattered on the sands: Not that I think the opinion of our new <hi>Chiliasts</hi> so deadly and pernicious in it selfe, as to make ship-wrack of their own or others faith; far be it from me to be guilty of so much uncharity, as to lay so deepe a charge upon my fellow Christians; for what prejudice is it to me, if the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114837:8"/>souls of Martyrs get the start of me in resuming their bodies a thousand years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, if, in the mean while my soul be at rest in a Paradise of blisse? And what can it import any mans salvation to determine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Saints reign with Christ on Earth, or in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, whiles I know that in either they are happy? Surely, in it's own terms, the Tenet seems to carry no great appearance of offence; but all the danger is in that train of strange Paradoxes, and uncouth consequences, which it draws in after it; specified in the following Discourse; and in the ill u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses that are made too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114837:9"/>of it, by some ill-advised and mis-taken Clients: Whereof some vainly imagining this Reign of the Saints already begun,
<note n="5" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lights at</hi> Walton.</note> cast off Scriptures, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances as utterly use-lesse, and please themselves in a conceited fruition of their happy Kingdom, and an immediate cōversation with the King of Glory: Others construing all mutations which befall the Church; as either the harbingers, or severall stages of their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours approach to his new Kingdom, and theirs, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud themselves in their imminent and already-des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cried glory; rejoycing to tel us how far he is on his way;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114837:9"/>and (lest we should appeal to our own eyes in so im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant a case) tell us that this object is not for our discerning,
<note place="margin">Zions <hi>joy in her King</hi> pag. 24, 25, &amp;c.</note> but for qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed persons only; men, not like the ordinary sort of professors, who are of a low, poor, pufillanimous spirit, but for such only, as are deepely engaged in the Churches Cause, and sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in her Troubles, and Sorrows; whereas, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if those which suffer most may be allowed to be the most quick-sighted, it may easily be known whose eys we may best trust for intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence. Hence have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed heavie censures, &amp; harsh entertainmēts of the other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114837:10"/>affected; and an insul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation upon dissenting bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, as the oppressed and down troden enemies of this Kingdom of Christ.</p>
            <p>I desire not to aggravate either these or any other inconveniences which doe usuall attend this opinion, as one that wishes rather to heale, then to corrode the publique soars.
<note place="margin">The inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Author in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing discourse.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let mee therefore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingage my Reader, not to mis-take my discourse or my intentions; For my part, I am perswaded in my foul, that the coming of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour is neer at hand; and that before that great Day God hath decreed, and will yet effect a more happy and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114837:10"/>flourishing condition of his Church here on earth, then we yet see; which I do hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pray for, and hopefully expect; ambitiously suing to my God, that my poor endeavours might bee thought worthy to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute any thing to so blessed a purpose; But, for the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularities of the time, and manner, I both have learn'd, and do teach silence. And if any man think he hath suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient intimation of either, or both of these, in the words of holy Scripture; yet since those clauses are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved in some obscurity, &amp; may afford multiplicity of sense; my desire and whole drift is, to beseech him to<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114837:11"/>suspend his judgement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning these so deepe and intricate Doctrines, till God shall be pleased to clear them by apparent events. And in the mean time to rest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, with those evident and unquestionable truths of the Gospel, which the Church of Christ hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto unanimously taught and maintained; wherein he shall doe that which may happily conduce both to the Churches peace &amp; his own.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114837:11"/>
            <head>THE REVELATION <hi>Ʋnrevealed.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>1</label>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Prophesies especially before they be fulfilled,
<note place="margin">That this one diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult place of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alone, expresseth this thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand years reign.</note> are no other then Riddles, needes no other proof then (amongst other) the two dark passages of the <hi>Revelation;</hi> the one concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Number and Name of the Beast 666: the other concerning the Thousand years reign of the Saints;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114837:12"/>either of which I may bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly say, many have guessed at; but no man living hath yet been ever able fully to unfold.</p>
               <p>Our businesse is with the later; set forth by the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Disciple,
<note place="margin">Rev. 20.4.5.</note> and Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Prophet, St. <hi>John</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the shutting up of his divine Revelation; out of the literall sense whereof, not a few in these later times have been raysed to such a confidence of the speedy accomplishment of this new Kingdome, as if they did already see the clouds breaking under the glorious feet of their returning Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and the chaires of this blessed State set ready
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114837:12"/>for their Enthronization; How many have I heard joyfully professing their hopes of an imminent share in that happy Kingdome; yea some have gone so far, as already to date their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from New <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and to subscribe themselves glorified: whose ungroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded credulity may receive some just correction, if they shall but see the strange va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of construction, which this supposed earthly Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty hath undergone from men as wise in their owne opinion, as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves.</p>
               <p>Whereunto that I may make the better way, I shall lay this for an undoubted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114837:13"/>ground, that there is no Passage in the whole book of God, wherein this Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenary reign of Saints is punctually expressed, save onely this of the Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For; as for those 66 texts alledged by <hi>Alstedius,</hi> and the late Herald of Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, joy, they are too ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to make out such a specialty, both of the terme, and the personall admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration which is contended for; and besides have been by the judgement of all al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed antiquity, and all Christian Authors, till the fag-end of this last Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, understood of the spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall beauty, and glory of the Evangelicall Church,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114837:13"/>under the happy times of the Gospell: Whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever shall bee pleased to take a strict view of these severall Scriptures, shall finde them onely to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the calling of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the conversion of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of rich graces pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out upon beleevers, Gods gracious protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and enlargement of his Christian Church, the subjugation, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the publique e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies thereof; all which may well stand without any relation to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended dominion of the raised Martyrs, or changed Saints: So as I cannot but
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114837:14"/>wonder to see Christian au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors so apt to humour the refractory Jewes, in a lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall construction of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall predictions of the restauration of that pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous and secular glory, which they have hitherto fondly dreamed of, and hath been hitherto unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously decryed by all the ancient and late Doctors of the Christian Church: and to see these Evangelicall promises thus carnally drai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a wrong channell: which certainly who so shal stand upon in so grosse a sense, may as well contend that the new <hi>Jerusalem</hi> shal really have twelve gates of twelve pearles, and streets
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114837:14"/>of pure gold,
<note place="margin">Rev. 21.21</note> &amp; the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the wals all manner of precious stones: And if these be figurative, why should the other be lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>2</label> But that Scripture which might seem to beare most weight in this subject,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie of</hi> Daniel <hi>improperly alleaged to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose.</hi>
                  </note> is the prophesie of <hi>Daniel,</hi> who in the construction of the favourers of the Millenarian opinion, is pretended to speak particularly of the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall reign of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ, of his destruction, of the happy deliverance and peace of the faithfull under the Gospel, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a speciall designation of the punctuall Time
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114837:15"/>wherein that man of sin shall be revealed; &amp; wherein Gods people shall enjoy rest and happinesse, both in the beginning and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination thereof: Insomuch as, besides <hi>Alstede,</hi> our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Mede,</hi> in a Latine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuscript of his, which came lately to my hands concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Revelation of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist, grounds his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon <hi>Daniels</hi> Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie; not a litle blaming some late Expositors for turning the stream of those predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions another way; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving a due reverence to so great and Eagle-ey'd Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, I dare appeal to all unbiassed judgements, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it do not best suit with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114837:15"/>all the circumstances of those aenigmaticall prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies of <hi>Daniel,</hi> to confine their relations only to the Jewish Church, making their utmost extent to be the death of the <hi>Messiah,</hi> &amp; the destruction of <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> without any further medling with the state of the Church Evangelicall; saving onely in that one touch of the second com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Christ to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein both the whole Church and World is joyntly concerned: To make therefore the fourth Monarchy to be the Roman tyrannizing over the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Church under the Gospel, and the little Horn
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114837:16"/>with eyes to be the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ of the last times, and to draw the computation of the times mentioned unto an accordance to an imagined calculation, may seem to be no other then a strayning of the Text beyond the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Author: sure we are, that al those prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall predictions were lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and really fulfilled to and upon the Jewes, under the reigne of those Kings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst whom the Grecian Empire of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great was shared; and that in the just times which were designed: but upon what grounds we may stretch them further to a re-accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishment in these last times
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114837:16"/>it is neither easie nor safe to determine.
<note place="margin">O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>colam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pad. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Danielem l. 2.</note> Two things must be yielded, First, that those descriptions which are made by Divines of that cruell Tyran, and persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> may well by just allusion be applyed to the Antichrist under the Gospel; secondly, that it hath pleased the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God to make use of the same expressions in <hi>Iohns</hi> description of times, which had formerly been taken up by <hi>Daniel;</hi> but hereupon to inferre a revolution of the same condition of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Church in the last age of the world, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects of her enemies &amp; se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral events seems strange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inconsequent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:114837:17"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>3</label> The probablest and most urgent passages of the Prophet DANIEL,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The most urgent passage of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie of</hi> Daniel <hi>cleared.</hi>
                  </note> and those which are most stood upon by the fore na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Authors, are <hi>Dan. 12.11, 12. And from the time that the daily sacrifice shall be taken away, and the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination that maketh deso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late set up, there shall be a thousand two hundred and ninety dayes. Blessed is the man that waiteth, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the thousand three hundred and five and thirty dayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where these two things are taken by these Exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors for granted; 1. That the taking away of the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sacrifice, and this desola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114837:17"/>abomination, is to be understood of the last de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of <hi>Hierusalem</hi> by <hi>Titus.</hi> 2. That the days there mentioned are to be understood to be so many yeares: which shall immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately succeed in the processe of the Evangelical Church; So as by <hi>Alsteds</hi> confident account the destruction of <hi>Jerusalem</hi> falling upon the 69th. year of Christ, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently begins the reckoning of the thousand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ninety propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call dayes, that is so many Yeares; which do expire in the Year of Christ 1359, about which time divers worthy persons (say they) began to oppose Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114837:18"/>impiety: From this period, they tell us we must begin to compute the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond number mentioned by <hi>Daniel,</hi> which is the 1335 dayes, that is, Years; which shall bring us unto the Year of Christ, 2694. In which, saith <hi>Alstedius,</hi> the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Years of the Saints raigne spoken of in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation shall have end, and they being ended, the war of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> shall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, which the last Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment supervening shall put to an end: So then, take from these 2694 yeares, one thousand yeares of the Saints raigne; there remains 1694; In this year then or sooner (saith he) the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114837:18"/>years of the happy raigne of the Saints shall take their beginning. But what a weak and sandy foundation is this whereon to raise so high a structure? A foundation meerly laid upon a mis-constructive conjecture; For, what if that desolation mentioned be not that of <hi>Titus?</hi> what if those dayes be not years? where are we then for the time of our Millenary raign? Let us then obtain leave to inquire a little into both these. And for the first; It is more then probable by all circumstances, that this desolating abominatiō here spoken of is the same with that, which is fore-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114837:19"/>
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.13, 14. wherein the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of the daily sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and the desolation specified, are foretold by the Angel, interpreting the vision; and the very same time limited for the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it; Both which are accordingly with much clearnesse of indubitable truth, accomplished in that persecuting tyran <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes;</hi> Compare we the texts and the times: <hi>He</hi> (saith the Angel) <hi>shall think to change times and lawes and they shall be giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en into his hand untill a time,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 7.25.</note>
                  <hi>and times, and the dividing of time.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 8.11, 12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By him the daily sacrifice
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114837:19"/>was taken away, and the place of his Sanctuary was cast down;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Seven times.</hi> i. <hi>seven years.</hi> Dan. 4.16.</note>
                  <hi>&amp; an host was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him against the daily sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, by reason of trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression, and it cast down the truth to the ground, and it practised and prospered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now what are a time, times, and a parcell of time by <hi>Daniels</hi> own exposition (<hi>Dan.</hi> 4.16.) but three years and some days? and what are those three years and few dayes, but those three years and ten dayes, wherein the rage of perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution continued upon the Jewes till the happy restau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Gods Worship wrought by <hi>Judas Macabae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us;</hi> who in seven moneths
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114837:20"/>and ten dayes after this forced the confirmation of it from the persecutors. And who is the man that shall do this great mischiefe intimated? Even that bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Antiochus,</hi> which is so exactly deciphered by the Prophet, as if he meant to fore-stall all question that might arise concerning him in the following generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<note place="margin">Dan. 8.8,</note> For it cannot be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that the great horn of the Goat which was the third Monarch,
<note place="margin">9.</note> was <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Great; which horn being broken, the four horns that arose in stead thereof, were unquestiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly those four Kingdomes towards the four coasts of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114837:20"/>Heaven, amongst which that Grecian Monarchy was divided; which were of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> towards the South fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to the share of <hi>Ptolomee Philadelphus,</hi> of <hi>Syria</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the North which fell to <hi>Seleucus Nicanor,</hi> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon</hi> towards the West, which fell to <hi>Cassander,</hi> and of <hi>Asia</hi> the lesse to the East, which fell to the share of ANTIGONUS; Now out of one of these (saith the Prophet) that is <hi>Seleucus Nicanor,</hi> King of <hi>Syria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">8. vers. 9.</note> shal arise that little horn, the cruell <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> who shall make such wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full havock amongst Gods select Nation, the Jews; styled the people of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114837:21"/>Saints of the most High:
<note place="margin">Dan. 7.27.</note> in taking away the daily sacrifice, and defacing the Sanctuary: whose grievous persecution for the first stage of it, was of that pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall duration. And to matter yet more cleare, if we shall compare <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.14. with this instanced text of <hi>Dan</hi> 12.7. we shall find the number of the dayes pitcht upon to be the very same <hi>for a time, times, and halfe a time.</hi> So as the 1290 days immediately specifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed make up that three years and a halfe. Wherein the fury of <hi>Antiochus</hi> his perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution shall continue; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any relation to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Titus,</hi> which is preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114837:21"/>by these Authours to make good their imagined cōputation. Reverend <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> (whose judgement I so much honour, that I reckon him amongst the best Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of Scripture, since the Apostles left the earth) is willing to construe this of the last desolation of the Jewes by the Roman Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, but knows not what to make of the dayes speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; professing that he is no <hi>Pythagorean</hi> for matter of numbers; and therefore contents himselfe to take this 1290 dayes onely <hi>pro longo temporis tractu;</hi> for some long indefinite tract of time; But whereas <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stede</hi> builds his conceit upon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114837:22"/>the succession of these two numbers;
<note place="margin">Quidam separant sed perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram dies 1290 &amp; 1335. Nam certum est pro eodem accepi. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin. in loc. Dan. Ser.</hi> 12.</note> making the 1335 dayes (.i. Years) to follow after the former 1290; out of both making up his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished number of the Saints raigne, expiring; <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> checks him with a plain <hi>(perperam)</hi> and resolves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a <hi>(certum est)</hi> that both these numbers are coinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and are to be taken for one and the same with that small addition of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and later summe of years to the former; which if it be yielded, we are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to seek for our calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the thousand years wherein the Saints must raign upon earth. Onely one main rub seems to lye
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114837:22"/>in our way, which we must be carefull to remove:
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.15.</note>
                  <hi>Our Saviour himselfe speakes of the abomination of desolation, spoken of by</hi> Daniel <hi>the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, standing in the holy place; as a thing in his dayes yet to come:</hi> and therefore with undoubted relation to the Roman Army, led by <hi>Titus,</hi> and to the finall sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Jerusalem:</hi> All which I do willingly grant, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any the least derogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from that former veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: For what is the holy place but the Temple of <hi>Jerusalem?</hi> and what is the abomination of desolation but the Idolatrous heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish destructive Army? such was both that of <hi>Titus,</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:114837:23"/>and that of <hi>Antiochus;</hi> The place then of <hi>Daniel,</hi> to which our Saviour alludes (with charge to him that reads to observe) is not the fore-mentioned text now insisted upon, but <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.27. wherein the Angel, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the end of the designed weeks, tels us of the finall destruction of the City and the Sanctuary, which in the just time was accordingly fulfilled; so as this passage of prophesie hath no affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at all with that of the 12th. of <hi>Daniel;</hi> being not so much before it in place, as after it in time. Yet if the event had not punctually made good every jot of this prediction so construed, as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114837:23"/>we have declared, there might be some doubt of the sense contended for; but now, the issue of the things did so evidently answer to the words thus interpreted, as one would think there could be no place left for contradiction; For (as <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Rolloc,</hi> and <hi>Deodati</hi> have clearly computed it, to my hands) from the time that <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> began to set up Idolatry at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> untill the time wherein he was compelled by the victorious <hi>Macabaeus,</hi> both to permit, and allow, and ratifie the reformation thereof by his charter, there passed three years,
<note place="margin">2 Macab. 11.33.</note> seven moneths, and about thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114837:24"/>dayes, which amount to the thousand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ninety dayes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. Vers. 11.</p>
               <p>And from the setting up of that Idolatry, if we rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon to the time of the full deliverance of Gods people from the yoke of that ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, it will fall upon the second number mentioned. Vers. 12. wherein that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Antiochus</hi> was taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by death; which makes up the thousand, three hundred, and five and thirty dayes: which day who so should live to see is declared to be blessed for his happy freedome, and comfortable enjoying of the holy worship of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:114837:24"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>4</label> And now what is here in the letter of <hi>Daniels</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>These pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tended do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be grounded upon</hi> Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel <hi>by way of Type, or Analogie: Inquiry made whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther since the words are single, the sense be cleere.</hi>
                  </note> that doth but look towards the thousand years raigne of the Saints upon earth? Surely not one syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable that may without a violēt angariation be drawn to such a sense. And if <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stede</hi> shall pretend that these mysteries of the latter times concerning the Antichrist, and the time of the Saints raigne, are to be found in <hi>Daniel,</hi> not in the expresse letter, but in a way of Type, or Analogie, because he meets with the same phraseology of time, and the like description of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and things in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelists Revelation, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:114837:25"/>he finds in <hi>Daniels</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie; Surely he had need of greater authority for the warrant of such application, then I fear can be produced: and if that were yielded, yet that which we are wont to say of similitude is veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied much more in prefigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, that they are not intended to hold univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally; and in short, Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicall Divinitie is not to be trusted for marter of proofe. What Mysteries there may be in numbers, and upon what reason it hath pleased the Spirit of God to take up the same termes of numeration for dayes, moneths, yeares and times in the case of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:114837:25"/>Christian Church, which he made use of in the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish, I suppose it were two much presumption in any man to determine. And if the events of things be the best Commentaries upon prophesies, how unanswe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable those have proved to the computations and sense of our new Chiliasts, shall in due place be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest. Now if there be any other amongst those 65 places alleaged by <hi>Alste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> wherein the favourers of the Millenarian-raigne can place any confidence for the evicting of their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I should be glad to see it driven up to the head: For my part, I must syncerely
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:114837:26"/>professe I see none that can so much as raise, much lesse settle my beliefe: Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing then (as we well may) that this place of <hi>Revel.</hi> 20. stands alone; let us inquire whether the sense of it be so cleare, as that we may with good assurance build upon it, for the certainty of our resolution concerning the state of the whole world, and particularly of all Gods Saints for the space of a whole thousand yeares, lost hitherto in the vulgar account of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Divines. Surely there can be but one truth, and what ever fals beside it, is but vain opinion; as when two points are fixed, there
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114837:26"/>can be but one direct line drawn betwixt them, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bewray a manifest va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation, and obliquity: The Starres because they keep a regular course yield most certain observations of their site and motions; but the clouds which are raised out by vapours, and carried by windes, how farre they are from affording a true judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; let every Almanack witnesse, now whether this conceit be a starre or a cloud shall appeare by that which followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>5</label> Some Expositors then and those, neither few,
<note place="margin">The divers constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the thousand years of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans shut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up.</note> nor meane, have taken the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeares of Satans shut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:114837:27"/>up to be the same thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand wherein the Saints shal raigne: Others, not few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, make the Saints raigne to follow this binding of Satan for many hundreds of yeares; And for the time of this chaining up of Satan, some take the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeares for a long time, but indefinite,
<note place="margin">Fulk in loc. Deodati in loc.</note> so <hi>Fulk</hi> and <hi>Deodati;</hi> others construe it literally, of that determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate number of years spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, some define it to be the whole time since the first publishing of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel to the end of the world, so <hi>Nicolaus Zegerus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zegerus, Sa, Estius, in locum.</note>
                  <hi>Emma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel Sa</hi> and <hi>Estius.</hi> Some determin it to be the whole time of the Gospel publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed untill the days of their
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:114837:27"/>Antichrist;
<note place="margin">Ribera in locum. Haymo l. 7. in Apoc.</note> w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> should be three years &amp; an half before the judgment; so <hi>Ribera</hi> out of <hi>Augustine,</hi> so <hi>Haymo</hi> and <hi>Joannes Gagnaeus</hi> a Divine of <hi>Paris.</hi> Some define this number of the 1000 years to begin the 36 year or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts after our Saviours death, when the Jewish Church being overthrown, Satan rushed impetuously upon the Church Christian, and was restrained till the days of <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> so <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius;</hi> some define it to begin from the time of <hi>Constantine</hi> (whom Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives to be that Angell, which coming down from Heaven, and having the keyes of the bottomlesse
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114837:28"/>pit lay'd hold on the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, and bound him in chaines) till the thousand years expired; which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the 1300<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. year of Christ, in the days of <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> the eighth, and the <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman</hi> Empire, so <hi>Napier,</hi> and <hi>Brightman,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Foxe;</hi> some reckon it from first preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel by Christ, and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles untill the time of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the 7th, (otherwise called <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> and the time of Satans losing to be 400 or 500 yeares, so <hi>Dent:</hi> Others, ending the time of Satans shutting up in the year 1300, make the time of his rage to be an houre, a day, a moneth, and a year,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:114837:28"/>that is about 390 years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, so <hi>Brightman,</hi> some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers make the loosing of Satan to be when <hi>Mahomet</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> grew so great; which was at the end of the thousand years after Christ; in all which time the syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere doctrine was taught, till Antichrist came, in which the doctrine of the sacrifice of the Masse, and the doctrine of Merits, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions, &amp;c. so <hi>Fulk;</hi> some place the beginning of Satans binding, upon the year 1517; when the witnesses were raised; for that, from that time all People have not generally drunk any new poyson of heresie, which mightweaken
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:114837:29"/>or overthrow their faith, so <hi>Matthaeus Cotterius;</hi> some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers imagine the beginning of this chaining up of Satan to be after the taking of <hi>Rome</hi> by the <hi>Gothes,</hi> and after <hi>Augustulus,</hi> whowas the last Emperor of the West: affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming (though upon fickle grounds) that after the fall of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire; yea after <hi>Mahomet,</hi> there was peace in the Church for a 1000 years; so as Satan was bound, and shut up in the bottomlesse pit, till this last age now passed. So <hi>Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na:</hi> Others hold that this thousand yeares of Satans binding up is not yet begun, but shall be in this age wherin the Saints raign shal
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:114837:29"/>enter about the year 1694. So <hi>Alstedius</hi> and his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers.</p>
               <p>These are some of those varieties of constructions (for if I listed to look after them, it were easie to cloy the Reader with many more; these tendred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to me suddenly, and as it were unsought) which have passed concerning the thousand yeares captivity of Satan, whereby it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the Spirit of God to make way to the thousand yeares raign of the Saints; In the determinatiō where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, there is no lesse multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst learned and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Interpreters: Some
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:114837:30"/>few whereof I shall lay forth before my Reader.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>6</label> And first concerning the time of this raigne;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The divers constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the thousand years reigne of the Saints.</hi> Haymo in Apocalyps. lib. 7.</note> A thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand (saith <hi>Haymo</hi>) is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect number, and therefore, by a thousand yeares, we understand the present life, and the future: Now the Saints raign by faith; and in the day of Judgement there raigne shall not be terminated, but receive a glorious augmentation. So he.</p>
               <p>To the same purpose, saith <hi>Colladon;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Colladon in Apoc. 20.</note> the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand years are the whole se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of time here in this world, in which there shall be alwayes a Church of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:114837:30"/>Christ; As the faithfull have lived, and raigned with Christ 1000 years, that is in the whole space of this life, so they shall raign with Christ 1000 yeares in the whole duration of the world to come. And if this seem too large; surely these men do not shoot further over, then <hi>Joannes Brocardus</hi> shooteth short; who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracteth the thousand years after the establishment of the Gospel into a thousand days, here on earth; as contrarily <hi>Jonas</hi> his forty dayes were stretched out into forty yeares.</p>
               <p>Of those that hold not fit to divide the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the present and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:114837:31"/>life; some understand the 1000 years raign to be understood of the flourish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing estate of the Church militant, during the time of Satans captivity; for all the faithfull (say they) do in a sort live and raigne with Christ here on earth, when they overcome the world by faith; so Mr. <hi>Dent;</hi> some againe take it of the whole time between the first comming of Christ, and the second; so <hi>Occolam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padius in Daniele.</hi> Others, waving the present life, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine it to be meant of that glorious Kingdome, which the souls of the Saints en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy in heaven untill the day of Judgement; so <hi>Mariana;</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:114837:31"/>so <hi>Estius;</hi> and, <hi>Fulk</hi> to the same purpose, thus. These Martyrs being delivered from the calamities of this miserable life by the first death; and being taken up into heavenly joyes, they live and raign still, with Christ through the whole thousand years, so long as Satan shall remain in bonds; Not that after that thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeares they shall die, but to expresse how great a benefit it was to the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be all that while in happinesse; Thus hee, without any supposition of a preceding Resurrection; <hi>Joannes Piscator,</hi> as going yet further (even halfe the Millenary way) so construes
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:114837:32"/>it, as that it is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood of the raised Martyrs and their ensuing glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; This (saith he) is the singular happinesse of the Martyrs of Christ, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore these 1000 years en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured persecution; even, their Resurrection, which shall be before the generall Refurrection; and their raign in heaven with Christ for a thousand yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Resurrection of the rest.</p>
               <p>Of those which take this 1000 yeares raigne to be in this life below, there is no small variety of constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<note place="margin">Flac. Illir. Gloss. in Apoc.</note>
                  <hi>Illiricus</hi> takes it to be an inversion of sense, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate being set before the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:114837:32"/>subject, the relative before the antecedent; so as the order of the sense should be thus; I saw the soules of those that worshipped not the beast, &amp;c. and that dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Christ to live and raign with him, and to set on their thrones, and judge the wicked; raigning with Christ spiritually, in suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring bodily; as those who by their Martyrdome for Christ, shall raigne and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph (all the time of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans repression) over him, and his wicked Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aretius</hi> thus, They lived again, and raigned with Christ; that is, their cause was found just before him,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:114837:33"/>and they were openly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted and pronounced Saints.</p>
               <p>The thousand years raign (saith <hi>Ribera</hi>) is not to be referred to those which worshipped not the beast, for he speakes not of them as dead; but is to be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the souls of those, which had been Martyred for the testimony of Jesus; that is, to those, who, when he wrote this, had suffered death for Christ. So he. But others take it for a later reckoning:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Brightman.</hi> Apocal.</note> This raigne of a 1000 years (saith <hi>Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>) was to begin where the former period ended; that is in the year 1300; wherein the continuance of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:114837:33"/>the truth is promised to be for 1000 yeares, after the restitution of it in these parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> whose is the first resurrection; we onely have seen three whole hundreds of it past, since the first Resurrection; Thus he.</p>
               <p>Not so, saith Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Corton <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>surrection of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es.</hi>
                  </note> but after the destruction of Antichrist the Saints shall enjoy that liberty a 1000 years together; not any one of them, but men of the same spirit shall raign with Christ, 1000 yeares in the government of the Church upon earth:</p>
               <p>Raign with him; that is, execute not their own go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment but the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Christ.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:114837:34"/>
               <p>Nay; saith <hi>Alstede, Mede,</hi> and <hi>Archer,</hi> that sense fals too short; but the bodies of the Martyrs and Saints shal rise again in the beginning of those thousand yeares, before the universall and last resuirection; and shall raigne here with Christ up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth; as being appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Governours of the Church with Christ.</p>
               <p>No, they shall not rise in their bodies (saith Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi>) but there shall rise men of the same spirit; who shall have the Judicature and Government of the Church together with these Angels or Messengers, and Ministers of God; those that were branded before
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:114837:34"/>for Hereticks, they shall be the onely men to be fit to have Crownes on their heads, and <hi>Independent</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment committed to them. Thus he.</p>
               <p>But I may not tire the Reader too much with the enumeration of these dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences; some take this thousand yeares raigne to take beginning after the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond resurrection, whom Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> absolutely rejects.</p>
               <p>Others in the other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream imagine themselves, now already raigning with Christ; their resurrection or change to be already pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; and themselves glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and possessed of the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:114837:35"/>new <hi>Jerusalem</hi> descended from heaven: who if they do find in themselves these high workings of the spirit, which they professe; and be so farre transported with these raptures, as to think themselves already in their new heaven. I should not be more apt to wonder at their extasies then to pitty their glory.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mede,</hi> Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarium Apocalyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti cap. part. 2.</note> Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> makes the 1000 yeares raigne to be the day of a more visible, and apparent judgement; circumscribed with two conspicuous Resurrections, as two limited termes; It shall be (saith he) begun first with the particular, and timely judgement of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ, and other enemies
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:114837:35"/>of the Church, then remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning alive, with the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous appearance of our Lord Jesus Christ, in flames of fire; and at length, after the Kingdom of a thousand yeares granted to his holy Spouse, the new <hi>Jerusalem</hi> here on earth, and others, that shal afterward be born, this great day now drawing to an end, shall be finished, (after the letting loose of Satan, and utter destruction of the Churches enemies) with the generall resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and judgement of all the dead; which being performed, the wicked shal be thrust down to hell to be tormented everlastingly, and the Saints translated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:114837:36"/>heaven to raigne eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally with Christ. So he.</p>
               <p>Shortly, some hold this raigne of Christ with his Saints for the 1000 years shall be personall, and visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. So <hi>Mede,</hi> and <hi>Archer,</hi> Others that this while, Christ shall raigne visibly in Heaven, invisibly upon Earth; so <hi>Alstedius:</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers leave it <hi>in medio</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther personall or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Boroughs</hi> in <hi>Hose.</hi> Lect. 7.</note> so Mr. <hi>Boroughs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And lastly, whereas this Kingdome of the thousand years, relates to the Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; some hold the first Resurrection spiritually to be understood of rising from sin by a spirituall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation. So <hi>Fulk,</hi> and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:114837:36"/>
                  <hi>Aretius.</hi> Others take it of a bodily resurrection of some elect persons, before the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neiall; as <hi>Alstede</hi> and <hi>Mede;</hi> Others take it of a Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Churches, when recovered from then Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staticall, and dead estate in Idolatry; so Mr. <hi>Cotton:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cotton <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es.</hi>
                  </note> Others lastly, make the first resurrection to be the glorification of the souls of the elect; and the second at the generall day, the ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to their perfect blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse both in soules and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; so <hi>Gagnaeus:</hi> Some appropriate this first resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and raigne to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs onely; others enlarge it to all the Saints; Now, Lord, where are we? what
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:114837:37"/>Reader doth not find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe lost in this wildernesse of opinions? Or what living man can, in such diversities of probable judgements, say, this, not the other, is the sense of the holy ghost? It was a wise and true word of that Father, <hi>Melius est dubitare de occultis, quàm li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigarede incert is:</hi> It is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to doubt of things hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den then to quarrell about things uncertain; And to the same purpose is that dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and moderate coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of <hi>Deodati;</hi> In all this prophesie (saith he) it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more sure to expect and stay for the explication of the event, then to give it without any certain ground;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:114837:37"/>which seasonable advise if it had been accordingly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by many of our zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous compatriots, had saved me the labour of this not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-pleasing discourse.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>7</label> But when I saw so many wel-minded Christians by a credulous trust of some modern authority,
<note place="margin">The history of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Chiliasts briefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</note> strongly carried back into the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ancient Chiliasts, which was so many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren years ago hooted out of the Christian Church; and so passionately affected therewith, as that they run themselves into wild con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequents both of paradoxes in opinion, and resolutions in practise; I might not but
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:114837:38"/>break silence; and, if no more, yet charitably to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise them to a safe suspensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of judgement, in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter so abstruse, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeterminable. It is true that it is not a matter of faith; neither imports salvation, either way; so as here can be no warrant for the violation of charity in over bitter censures of either the defenders or oppugners of it; Yet withall, it must be granted to be such as (in that forme wherein it is maintained by some abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors) may draw in some dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Consectaries both of Act and Opinion; It would be bootlesse for me to look back at the ancient
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:114837:38"/>heresie of the Milliaries, as <hi>Austine</hi> cals them; to shew how that grosse error, which was first broached by the <hi>Epicurean,</hi> and (as <hi>Lindanus</hi> justly cals him <hi>Judaizing</hi> CERINTHUS; was in a more tolerable sense, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up not long after, by <hi>Papias</hi> Bishop of <hi>Hierapolis,</hi> reported by <hi>Irenaus</hi> to be an Auditor of St. <hi>John,</hi> and companion of <hi>Polycarpus;</hi> a well meaning man, but (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) of a mean judgement, as he is styled; <hi>mente non acri,</hi> as <hi>Nicepho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus;</hi> which yet rellished so ill with the Christians of those times, as that this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry passage of the Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was deemed by them a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:114837:39"/>probable ground to call the divine authority of this whole book into question, (as savouring too much of <hi>Cerinthus</hi>) But the Majesty which shined in that holy prophesie soone dispelled that cloud: and induced the Church to find a better sense of so obscure a clause, then the meerly literall; wherein yet some eminent Authors thought fit still to rest, as <hi>Irenaeus, Justin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, Tertullian, Lactantius;</hi> yea we are told by that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy an Orthodoxe <hi>Dionysi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Alexandrinus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>About the yeare of Christ</hi> 270. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos</hi> an <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bishop, wrote a book in those early times, to this purpose, which he called <hi>Elonchum
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:114837:39"/>Allegoristarum;</hi> wherein he too grosly maintained that thousand yeares raigne in all earthly pleasure and delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; seconded also by one <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion,</hi> the then famous ring-leader of that Sect; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst whom that reverend and holy <hi>Dionysius</hi> bent his style,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> in two books of the promises of God; confuting that Judaicall and literall construction of the large predictions of the outward happinesse of the Church; now by some revived; who not without a preface of the high respects which he gives to the Author, for his excellent parts, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, effectually oppugnes his mis-raised opinion; and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:114837:40"/>spends three dayes confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with <hi>Coracion,</hi> to so good a purpose, as that he brought him by strength of argumentation,
<note place="margin">Eccles. hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor. lib. 7. cap. 22, 23.</note> to cast a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and recant his former errour; all which is fully laid forth by <hi>Eusebius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet, after this, about the year 370, <hi>Apollinaris</hi> that exploded heretick, revives this Sect; and adds this errour to the company of many, much worse, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by him; which, say <hi>Baronius</hi> and <hi>Binius,</hi> was so condemned in him by a Councell held at <hi>Rome,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the year 373; <hi>ut postac omninò conticuerit;</hi> that it never so much as whispered since; but as it is better
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:114837:40"/>observed by <hi>Aretius,</hi> it held out to the times of <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erome,</hi> and <hi>Augustine;</hi> who upon all occasions refell it, and cry it down for a <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish</hi> fable: Ever since which time, till now of late, there hath been no noise at all of it, in the world; so as it hath lyen dead for this twelve hundred and forty yeares; and now is raised up out of the grave of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion by some that think themselves wiser then their predecessors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>8</label> But,
<note place="margin">The sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the doctrine of the late Millena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</note> forasmuch as it doth not so greatly concerne us to know what in this case hath been held by former Opinionists, as what is now
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:114837:41"/>insisted upon for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, let us both carefully inquire into the substance of this uncouth doctrine, lately taken up by some of our Brethren, and unparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally examine the grounds whereupon it is maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In his Book of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonall-raign of Christ on earth, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth &amp; proving that Jesus Christ toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Saints shall visibly possess a Monarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call State and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in this world, Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted &amp; sold by</hi> B. Allen, <hi>Anno</hi> 1643.</note> And for that I finde none hath laid forth this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion so fully, and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, as a late London-Divine, Mr. <hi>John Archer;</hi> one esteemed of so great sanctity and worth, as that no mean person doubted not to file him amongst men as precious as any the earth bore in his time; I shall fearlesly take his word for the point, in hand; and shall first sum up his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:114837:41"/>concerning this sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; and then shew the Improbabilities and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruities of it; the rather for that I perceive his concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons passe generally for the current Tener of the fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of this plausible opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>First,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>M.</hi> Archer <hi>abridged concerning Christ's kingdom &amp; comming.</hi>
                  </note> then he layes for his foundation, that there is a three-fold Kingdome of Christ; One Providentiall, which is that universall So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty by which Jesus Christ manageth the affairs of all the world, both in heaven, and earth; Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther spirituall, which is that Soveraignty which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises over the consciences of some people, and in spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:114837:42"/>the Elect; subduing them by his Word and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to an universall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of him; A third Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchicall, wherein Christ, when hee enters upon it, will governe as earthly Monarchs do; that is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versally over the World, and in a worldly, visible and earthly glory: not by tyranny, and oppression; and sensually, but with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, peace, riches, and whatsoever in and of the World is not sinfull: so as Christ shall administer this Soveraignty over all the Earth, in a visible, and worldy manner, for splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, riches, peace, &amp;c. though not in a fleshly or sinfull manner: hee thence
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:114837:42"/>descends to the considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the manner of this Kingdome of Christ, both in the extent, and qualities of it: The extent of it he makes to be unto all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable creatures, Angels, Devils and men: shewing that the high ones of the earth, Kings, and their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies shall fall before the Lord, both Sun and Moon. i. Majesty of an higher and lower rank shal vanish before him; he shal change all worldly custom, and so all Kingly glory; and set up a new, even his own glory. Secondly, for the opening of the quality of it; he makes a double day of judgment; one strict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:114837:43"/>take for a partiall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of some, not all; wherein many both Saints and sinners shall be judged, and that with great terrour, and solemnity; The other, generall, wherein all men and Devils shall be judged: bringing a world of Saints and Sinners first to the bar of that more partiall and strictly-taken Judgement, long before the Last and Generall Day.</p>
               <p>But even that former shall be, he saith, a Generall Judging (though not to the second death) of all the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly in the world; at least of all that will not stoop to Christ his Scepter; And secondly, ajudging to the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:114837:43"/>Saints alive who shall be blamed for their former failings.</p>
               <p>Now these two times and degrees of Judgment begin &amp; end Christs King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or Monarchies; so as all the time of his raigne may fitly be called a day of Judgment; wherein there is an evening and morning, answerable to the naturall day: In the evening or first part of Christs King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome there is first an end, or withdrawing and ceasing of the light and glory of the fore-going day; so Christs Kingdome shall begin with the withdrawing of Peace and Comfort, and in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing darknesse; in that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:114837:44"/>great troubles shall begin to arise upon those, who shall be the subjects of Christs Monarchy, both believing Gentiles and Jewes, with Israelites, or the ten Tribes, who shall be all converted, and greatly troubled; but when that trouble is at the height; then comes the beginning of Christs King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. AT the first setting up then of this Kingdome, Christ shall come from Heaven visibly; even as he went thither; which yet is not his last Comming to the last Judgment, but a middle comming betwixt the two other; For Christ, he saith, hath three com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings; The first when he
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:114837:44"/>came to take our nature; The second when he comes to receive his Kingdome, for the receiving of which he went to Heaven; The third when he comes to judg all and end the world: This second comming of Christ shall be long before his comming to the last judgment. In which second comming Christ will do these three things. First, he will raise up the Saints which are dead before this his comming, not onely such as have been Martyred as some think, but all Saints who have died in the Faith; for which cause he is said to come with all his Saints. <hi>Zecha.</hi> 14.5. But all the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:114837:45"/>dead which are not Saints, shall lye still in the dust, till the last and generall judgement, for the second death.</p>
               <p>The Saints which thus are raised in the first Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection shall not returne to a mortall state of body a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, nor yet be so perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glorified as they shall be afterwards; for then the people on earth could not bear their presence, for they shall shine as the Sun, but they shall be in a middle state, betwixt glory and mortality, as Christ was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Resurrection, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Ascension: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, he will destroy the wicked people on earth,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:114837:45"/>for they about the time of his comming shall combine against the Saints; and then will Christ suddenly sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise them to their ruine; now this ruine of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, shall not be as yet uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall, to every one; onely now he will ruine the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of them; and so he will break the head and the arme of them; as it was with the <hi>Egyptians</hi> at the red Sea; and the rest he will make slaves to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; And, it seems that some wicked shall be left for a seed to these Nations, because by the end of Christ's Kingdom, <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> shall rise against the Saints; which cannot arise
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:114837:46"/>out of such as prove hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, or excommunicated, for there shall be none such there; <hi>but these wicked ones left, shall be the Nations ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with iron, Revel. 2.27.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, he shal examine, blame and shame the Saints who are alive at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, if they be found to have walked loosly: He wil not kill them, nor change them in a moment, but shame them; therefore <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> exhorts to be holy, <hi>that we be not blamed at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.11.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>9</label> Now when Christ hath thus done,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>M.</hi> Archers <hi>opinion concerning Christ's withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven again, and the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment deputed to the Saints; with their priviledges.</hi>
                  </note> and put his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome into forme, he will withdraw to Heaven again,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:114837:46"/>and leave the Government to the dead Saints raised up: among whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles shall be chiefe; and they shal have the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of those Saints, which are found alive: that is, they and all believers shall rule the world, in which the twelve tribes shall be chief; and they shall not onely rule as Kings, but as Priests; that is, discipline their souls as wel as their bodies.</p>
               <p>Now for that it might seem to be no small dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage for the souls of Saints dead to be fetcht from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to live againe upon earth, with men, in their bodies; he tels us that it is likely the souls of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:114837:47"/>Saints are not in the highest Heaven, but in a middle place better then this world, but inferiour to the highest Heaven, which Place is meant by Paradise in the new Testament; which Paradise, he conceives, to be below the third Heaven, and therefore surely to be in the Region, or Element of fire, where the Sun, and Starres are, or in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Region of ayre, which is called Heaven in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
               <p>These <hi>Saints</hi> souls fetcht from this Paradise, and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with their bodies raised from the dead (which is the first Resurrection) they rule Christs Kingdom, even all
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:114837:47"/>of them; though some of them in more eminent place then others.</p>
               <p>The Persons that shall be governed, or the subjects of this Kingdome, shall be all that live upon earth, and the place they shall governe shall be the whole world; the Saints shall be ruled like the Israelites under <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wicked as slaves; Those ten of the twelve Tribes that are lost, shall be found out and made subjects of this Kingdome; The cities of the Tribes shall be built againe, especially <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem</hi> which shall be the most eminent city then in the world. The Israelites shall be first raised to this
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:114837:48"/>glory, and at <hi>Jerusalem</hi> wil Christ begin to shew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; and from the Israelites shall glory descend to the Gentiles.</p>
               <p>The priviledges of this Kingdome shall be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful: First, all the subjects of it that are freemen shall be holy, and not seemingly Saints, but true Saints, not any sinners. Nothing that defileth, shall be then, no hypocrite; no person ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, as proving bad; nor any of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of these Saints shall prove naught, but all shall be elect, and prove Saints, and the seed of the blessed; for if any of their issue should prove hypocrites,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:114837:48"/>or wicked persons, it would so affect them that they should not have everlasting joy; neither could sorrow, nor sighing fly away; now in these times there shall be no sorrow nor weeping: They shall be edified im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from God in Christ; The Sacrament is but to last till the next comming of Christ, to set up his Kingdome: Christ wil hold them up in fulness of grace, though not in full perfection of grace till the last generall judgement, or their translation to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p>There shall be a full and present answer to all their praiers, there being no sin to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:114837:49"/>keepe good things from them.</p>
               <p>There shall be a fulnesse of all temporall blessings, as peace, safety, riches, health, long life, or whatsoever can be had in this world.</p>
               <p>They shall have exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from all bodily trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</p>
               <p>Every one shall live an hundred years; no infant, nor any other shal die soon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; there shall be no sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, or grief to consume the strength; although a naturall death shall be, yet yet there shall be no violent or untimely death by any grief, sicknesse or trouble: Satan shall be wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained from tempting
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:114837:49"/>them to sin; or others to trouble them.</p>
               <p>Originall corruption shall be kept in, not to break forth into any grosse way. To which hee ads; they shall not be infected with Popery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>10</label> This for the evening or first part of Christs King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The latter part of this Kingdom of Christ set forth by M.</hi> Archer, <hi>both in the occasion, &amp; time of it.</hi>
                  </note> Now when this Kingdome of Christ hath lasted to many generations, the slaves and tributaries wil be grown to multitudes; these under the name of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> upon whom the Devil shall be let loose, shall be drawn by Satan to assault the Saints, which trouble shall not be long;
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:114837:50"/>it shall be suddain and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, but short; for Christ shall suddainly come from heaven, and with fire kil all the wicked ones, not lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving one of them alive upon earth. This assault of the wicked will Christ take for the occasion of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the last and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Judgement; before which he shall in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment change the bodies of all his Saints that are not dead but alive at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; and raise up the dead bodies of the Saints, who lived and died during this Kingdome of Christ; and they together with the changed Saints shall meet the Lord Jesus in the ayre,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:114837:50"/>comming again from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, never more to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>Then shall all the wicked be raised up from <hi>Cain</hi> to the last wicked man, that is found on the earth; and now shall be the judgment: which we call the day of Judgment, which being fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished the Saints shall be carried with Christ for ever into heaven; and the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed sent with the Devil into hell: which hell shall not be the same which is now so called; but another; this being now but as a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; that, the place of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution and torment.</p>
               <p>The hell that now is ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving onely to reserve con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:114837:51"/>demned spirits, which have no bodies till the execution at the last day; at which time this hel shal cease &amp; be swallowed up: The hel that shall be for torment, shall be all this lower and visible world of earth, waters, and the lower heavens reduced by God then to their first <hi>Chaos</hi> of confusion.</p>
               <p>Now this Kingdome of Christ, though for the Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or first part of it, it is expresly determined to last a thousand years, or ten ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations; yet the Dawning or latter part of it, is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed in Scripture how long it shall endure; but doubtless, but last a long time; and though called but
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:114837:51"/>a day of Judgement, yet it may last a thousand years, as the other is to do; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause, this is the time in which Gods Mercy, Justice, Truth, Power is to be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously revealed before all men and Devils; so as every sinner is to be silenced in his reasonings, or convinced; which must require much time.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this is the time in which Jesus Christ is to triumph and Lord it over all reasonable creatures, to be worshipt and acknowledg'd by every one in Heaven, Earth, and under the Earth.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the solemnitie of it were to little purpose if it were not to last long;
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:114837:52"/>as we deride great preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and pomp for a short show.</p>
               <p>Lastly, every act of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable creatures being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, shal not onely abide for ever in Heaven or Hell, but be revived and brought forth in that day before all the world; and all these acts from <hi>Adam</hi> to the last of mankind, shal be orderly &amp; cleerly proceeded inby books as in a Court of Justice.</p>
               <p>When all this is done, and the finall sentence pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced upon all creatures, both blessed and cursed, then will Christ resign his Kingdome to the Father, &amp; this world together with his Kingdom shall end.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:114837:52"/>
               <p>For the beginning of this Monarchie of Christ; it must be set up (saith he) the last in the World, after the other four are passed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the <hi>Roman</hi> is the last; That being divided into the Eastern and Western Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie; and out of the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stern ten Horns, or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms arising, and among them another little horne most blasphemous, which is the Papacie; when these ten Kingdoms, and the Papacie shall be put to an end, then is the beginning of this Kingdom of Christ, which (saith hee, by comparing of <hi>Daniel</hi> with the <hi>Revelation</hi>) shall be <hi>Anno</hi> 1666, the number of the Beast (onely
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:114837:53"/>the thousand (because it comes seldom) left out.)</p>
               <p>Three years and an half before this 1666, the Papall Power shall have support in <hi>Europe;</hi> all the ten King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms apostatizing to Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and yet one of them shall return to the Truth.</p>
               <p>In the yeares of Christ 1650, or 1656, the <hi>Israelites</hi> are to be delivered, by being called to Christianity, both <hi>Jews</hi> which were two Tribes, and the ten Tribes of <hi>Israel:</hi> Both which shall, after their conversion for 45 years after, suffer great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from <hi>Mahumetans,</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, Papists. Upon all which computations it is likely (saith he) that Christs
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:114837:53"/>comming from Heaven; and the raising the dead, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning his Kingdom, and the thousand years will be about the year of our Lord 1700: for it is to be about 45 yeares after 1650, or 1656.</p>
               <p>Now it being found out when Christs Kingdom, or the thousand yeares shal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, it is easie (hee saith) to guesse when the time of the last generall judgement, and the Worlds end shall be; which neither Angell, nor Christ himself as man, did in those days, when the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples asked the question, know, for it was lockt up in the Fathers secrets. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Christs sufferings, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:114837:54"/>Ascension, all the Fathers secrets were revealed to him, for hee was worthy, and he reveals them to the Churches by <hi>John:</hi> ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the meaning of <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els time, times, and half a time</hi> (which no creature could expound) <hi>to be</hi> 42 <hi>moneths, or</hi> 1260 <hi>dayes.</hi> He tels us expresly that his Kingdome should last after it was fully setled a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand years, and then should be a little disturbance; So as we have some comfort that there is hope the troubles of us Gentile-Christians shall cease about 666; But till those dayes we are like to see sad times, for it is to be feared that Popery shall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:114837:54"/>over-run <hi>Europe,</hi> and bring back under Papall power every King in <hi>Europe,</hi> and suppresse all their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers in every Kingdome; By this revolting of the Kingdoms to Popery, it comes that the witnesses are slain, and lie dead in the streets; But er'e Antichrist can have time to triumph four yeares, the witnesses shall be raised up, and one of the ten Kingdomes fall off from him, and ruine the city of <hi>Rome.</hi> But yet the Papacy shall breath and by degrees get head and joyn with <hi>Turk, Tartar,</hi> and the Christians in <hi>Europe;</hi> But from this danger wil Christ save all Christians by his
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:114837:55"/>comming, and setting up of his Kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>11</label> Thus have I faithfully related the opinion,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>That strain of errour which runs thorough the whole discourse of M.</hi> Archer; <hi>and is the common ground of this mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opinion.</hi>
                  </note> and summarily contracted the larger discourse of Mr. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> who upon the grounds of <hi>Alstedius</hi> and <hi>Mede,</hi> runs his own descant, plausibly enough; for every clause of his tractate calling up the Testimonies of the sacred Scripture; the severall alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations whereof, upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry passage, I could be most willing throroughly to scan, if I had lesse care to spare my self, then the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; for whose satisfaction that I may be neither un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonably tedious, nor in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:114837:55"/>sort deficient in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging of this subject: I shal first shew that universall strain and ground of errour, which runs through the whole writing of this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; then I shall note some of the chief of those bold paradoxall and unwarranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble assertions, which I meet with in this opinion and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course; in the third place I shal lay forth those strange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly improbable consequents which wil inevitably follow upon both; and lastly, I shall subjoyn such fair, safe, and orthodoxe constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as may be warrantably admitted of that darke pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage of Scripture, the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prison whereof is guilty of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:114837:56"/>this controversie.</p>
               <p>For the first; That which is the generall fault not of this Author onely, but of all other that look towards the Millenary way and indeed, the main ground of all their Heterodoxie in this point; is, that they put a meerly-literall construction upon the prophesies and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Scripture, which the holy Ghost intended onely to be spiritually understood; hence it is, that those fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent predictions, which we meet in every page of the Prophets, concerning the Kingdome of Christ, the re-edifying of the Jowish cities, the pompe and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence of restored <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:114837:56"/>their large priviledges and marvailous atchievements, are altogether drawn to a grosse, corporall, and sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicall sense; which the judgement of the whole Christian Church, second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the event, hath upon good grounds ever constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not of the letter, but the Spirit: I remember some thirty yeares or more agoe, a learned Gentleman, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Serjeant at law, a man very skilfull in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tongue, and that profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed no lesse acquaintance with the Lawes of God, then of man, published a large Volume concerning, not the imminent conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion onely, but also the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:114837:57"/>Royall State of the Jewes, their absolute, and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall Monarchy, their awfull Soveraignty over all the Kings of the earth, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their Empire, the splendour of their Court and Cities, gathering up to to this purpose, all the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious promises, which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre every where in the Prophets; at the sight whereof that deeply-judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious King <hi>James</hi> of preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous memory, was highly offended, and after the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>usall of some offensive pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages, commanded mee, then attending him to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the book to the Synode at <hi>Westminster</hi> then sitting, for their censure; who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:114837:57"/>a serious examination, with much Zeale unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously sentenced it to a speedy suppression, as that which did <hi>haerere in cortice,</hi> and savoured too strong of the flesh; as being to ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilely addicted to the letter. And now, those very texts, whole mis-understanding hath hitherto led the Jewes into a fools paradise by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting an earthly glory, are no less cōfidently taken up by the favourers of this opinion, as the main ground of their defence; For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, the Lord by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Zechariah</hi> hath said;
<note place="margin">Zech. 2.12.</note>
                  <hi>The Lord shall inherit</hi> Judah <hi>his portion in the holy land: and shall choose</hi> Jerusalem <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:114837:58"/>sing and rejoyce: ô daughter of Zion, for lo I come, and will dwell in the midst of thee, saith the Lord;</hi> This is by the Author of Zions joy applyed to that repaired and happy estate of the city <hi>Jerusalem</hi> at this second comming of Christ in glory whereas tho Ioro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher onely fore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stauration of that city and country after their then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present captivity, and under that figure describes the comfortable condition of the Evangelicall Church: So again by the Prophet <hi>Isaiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Isa. 65.9.</note> God saith; <hi>I will bring forth a seed out of Iacob, and out of Judah an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of my mountain, and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:114837:58"/>mine elect shall inherit it; and my Servants shall dwell there.</hi> This the same Author cites in a literall way to make good the resettlement of the Jewes in that ancient city of their inheritance; why doth he not as well adde that which followeth; <hi>And Sharon shall be a field of flocks, and the valley of Achor a place for the heards to lie down in; But ye are they that forsake the Lord, that forget my holy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain:</hi> Surely if one of them be appliable to the new <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> the other must be so also: The truth is, these prophesies have their reference either to Gods mercifull dealing with <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem</hi>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:114837:59"/>upon their returne from their <hi>Babylonish</hi> capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity; or by an usuall alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory, expresse his gracious purpose to the Church, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Gospell; without any respect at all to an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly re-establishment of the Jewish nation in their long-since forgotten possessions; It were as easie, as te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to passe thorough all those Scriptures which are wont to be alledged in this case; whereof I dare say there is scarce any one, whose either words or context do not evidently bewray their mis-applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or, if that did not, yet the event would; for as much as the time is now at
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:114837:59"/>hand, wherein these pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of the Generall call, and outward magnificence of these ancient people of God, should according to the construction of our new Chiliasts be either well for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or accomplished (as we shall see in the sequel) whereas there is not yet the least motion towards it in all the world.</p>
               <p>Besides some of their mis-construed Texts will necessarily crosse the way of us, upon occasion of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall passages which we are about to examine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>12</label> Of Paradoxes let it be the the first but not the least,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Yhe first Paradox of Millena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risme.</hi>
                  </note> that Christ the Son of God
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:114837:60"/>now glorified shall come and personally set up,
<note place="margin">A Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall state of Christ's Kingdom in a visible &amp; worldly manner.</note> and administer a Monarchicall state of a Kingdome here upon earth in a visible, and worldly manner, for splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, riches, peace, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I had thought we had heard him say, My King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is not of this world; now, to what world do rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and honour and earthly contentments belong, if not to this? If he governe as earthly Monarchs have done, in a worldly visible, earthly glory (such are the words) how is his Kingdom not of this world? Surely this is more then ever the very Jewes expected, or dreamed of; they have
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:114837:60"/>looked for a Messiah, that should exercise Kingly au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the world; but they never lookt for a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified Messiah to come down from heaven to rule upon earth. <hi>Zebedees</hi> wife certainly never thought of such a Kingdome, wherein her Sonnes should be the prime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Peers: Neither did the good Thiefe think of such a state, when be said, <hi>Lord, remember mee when thou commest into thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;</hi> we have heard of an absolute Soveraignty of Christ, as God; of a dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated Soveraignty as Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator; we have heard of his rule in the heart, of his rule in the Church, but of his
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:114837:61"/>Monarchicall rule in the world, for a whole thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeares in a worldly, visible, earthly glory, we never yet heard; and think it very strange newes to Christian eares.</p>
               <p>But much more strange news it is,
<note place="margin">Acts 3.21.</note> that all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets since the world began have spoken of this Marvai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Monarchy, and yet that we never heard of it in the writings of all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Doctors of the Christian Church, till this day: It is no whit strange, that Gods people should be abused by the feigned glos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of men, drawing those Scriptures which speak of Christs comming to the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:114837:61"/>judgement of the world, to the sense of that imaginary Kingdom which hath being no where but in their own brain: But without any intention of a formall confutation, I purpose one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to give some light touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es at those paradoxall and unwarrantable Positions, which meet with me in this discourse.</p>
               <p>That in this visible Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy of Christ he shall change all worldly customs,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Paradox. The change of all world ly custome and putting down king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly power.</hi>
                  </note> and put down all kingly power and greatnesse (how ever just) and set up a new; so as there shall be no more Lords but he; even as the earthly Monarchies swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed all kingly power un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:114837:62"/>them, may well passe for a sufficient Paradoxe: we grant indeed, there shall be none in competitiō with him, even in his spirituall rule; but that there shal be none in subordination to him in his supposed visible Monarchy, were too bold a word.</p>
               <p>That there shall be a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Judgment one a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand years before the other;
<note n="3" place="margin">Paradox. A double Judgment.</note> The one wherein many both Saints and sinners shal be judged,
<note place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> and that with great terrour and solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; which shall be a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Judging (though not to the second death,) of all the ungodly in the world;
<note place="margin">Pag. 13.</note> at least of all that will not
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:114837:62"/>stoop to Christ his Scepter; the other of all Devils and men,
<note place="margin">Pag. 14.</note> upon the expiration of those thousand years, in that universall appearance before God at that great Day; is an assertion as bold as groundlesse.</p>
               <p>We have heard of a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular doome passing upon every soule immediately upon the parting from this house of clay; and of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Iudicature in those common Assizes of the world; but of a middle sessions, betwixt both these, in which all the ungodly shall be arraigned, and sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced to a temporall death, or perpetuall vassalage, was never either spoken of by
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:114837:63"/>God, or heard of by men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>13</label> That there is a threefold comming of Christ.
<note n="4" place="margin">Paradox. A threefold comming of Christ.</note> The first, when he came to take our nature; the second, when he comes to receive his Kingdome; the third, when he comes to judge all, and end the world, may well passe for a Paradoxe, not inferiour to the rest; Besides, the Metaphoricall commings of Christ to any soul, or nation, whether in mercie, or judgement; we have ever heard of one comming of our Saviour, past, in humane weaknesse; another to come in divine power, and glory; but that there should be a third
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:114837:63"/>comming down from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to earth, betwixt these, is strange newes to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian eares; which were heretofore wont to be inu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to our old <hi>Apostolike, Athanasian,</hi> and <hi>Nicene</hi> Creeds; and to hear, <hi>From thence shall he come to judge the quick and the dead:</hi> No comming therefore till he come to Judgement; and that there may be no thought of an intermediate and partiall Judgement in the beginning of that thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand years, the Creed which we were wont to professe in our Baptisme, ran thus; <hi>We believe that in the end of the World, he shall come to judge the quick and the dead;</hi>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:114837:64"/>Lo, in the end of the world, not a thousand years before it.</p>
               <p>Let all good Christians stick close to their old Creeds,
<note place="margin">Jude 2.</note>
                  <hi>the faith which was once delivered to the Saints, and not suffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be carried away with every gale of new do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi> That of <hi>Tertullian</hi> is a sure rule, <hi>Primum verum;</hi> The first is true.</p>
               <p>Necessarily depending upon this,
<note n="5" place="margin">Paradox. A double Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> is that other grosse conceit of a double Generall Resurrection;<note place="margin">17.</note> The one, of those Saints which were dead before this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Christ which shal be raised up 1000 yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the rest at his next com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming;<note place="margin">18.</note>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:114837:64"/>the other of all flesh at the end of the World, and the final comming &amp; judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But whether that first Resurrection shal be onely proper and peculiar to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs that have died for the name of Christ, or common to all the Saints; Let our <hi>Chiliasts</hi> argue amongst themselves; their opinions doe no less disagree from each other, then they all from the Truth: <hi>Alass, good Martha, thou wert much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, when thou saidst con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thy brother Lazarus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 11.24.</note>
                  <hi>I know hee shall rise again in the Resurrection at the last day;</hi> Why, woman, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection of that Saint, thy Brother shal be 1000 years
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:114837:65"/>sooner thou thoughtest of; Neither did Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ever take notice of this first Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection of the Saints; whiles he adjures his <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy before God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.1.</note>
                  <hi>and the Lord Jesus Christ, who shall judge the quick and the dead at his appearing:</hi> For surely the Lord Jesus his judigng of the quick and dead (indefinitely spoken) must suppose a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection of all the dead whom he judgeth; but here (saith the <hi>Chiliast,</hi> is onely in Christs next appearing, a Resurrection of the dead Saints, and a judging of none but the wicked which are found alive; for their raising out of their graves is reserved for the last and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversal
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:114837:65"/>judgment; so as by that rule Christ should not at his appearing Judge both the Quick and the Dead:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>14</label> Answerable to this dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Resurrection is the Para<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doxe of Christs threefold Ascension, into Heaven;
<note n="6" place="margin">
                     <hi>Paradox. A threesold Ascension of Christ into heaven</hi> Pag. 23.24.</note> for (saith this Authour) when Christ hath thus put his Kingdome into forme, he will withdraw from earth to heaven againe; and leave the Government to the dead Saints raised up; They and all believers shall rule the world; And if these all shall govern, who are those that shall be governed? There are none left upon earth, but Saints raised to
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:114837:66"/>immortality, and Saints found alive, who are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect believers: and some few slaves spared frō death for servitude: See now what an honourable im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, and singular pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge and honour here is for Saints immortalized, and translated from death to life, to be the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of some sturdy, and rebellious vassals: In the mean time, Christ the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious King of his Church, is returned back into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and will governe the earth by his Deputies; what a mean conceit is this, which these men professe to have of the King of eternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? That he who hath said,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:114837:66"/>
                  <hi>Behold, I am with you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways even untill the end of the World,</hi> whose Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty fils heaven, and earth, should come down to put on his Kingdome here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, to be governed by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Delegates, and then with-draw to his heaven; what is this but poorly to circumscribe the infinite Majesty of heaven within the terms of a finite admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration? And now in this second Ascension we hear no newes of the atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his retinue; He that brought down the souls of his Saints, to wait upon him in this descent, for the receiving of this inferiour Kingdome, shall leave them
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:114837:67"/>behind him with their old (but new-raised) partners to spend 1000 yeares upon earth; at the end whereof, hee shall come downe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and fetch them up with him in his third As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cension to the highest hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. What an high pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption is this in flesh and bloud, to send the Son of God the Lord Jesus, from heaven to earth, and from earth to heaven, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an errand of their own making? when himself in his holy Scriptures never speaks but of a double as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of Christ; the one (which is past) from Mount O livet (where the impressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his sacred feet are stil
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:114837:67"/>said to be) forty dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Resurrection; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther future, when after the Generall Judgement of the world, he shall carry up all his elect with him to his heavenly glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>15</label> A literall Interpreter is no other then a slave to his syllables;
<note n="7" place="margin">Paradox. The totall roduction of the ten lost Tribes of Israel.</note> binding himself up to a mere sound of words, with neglect of the true sense intended; which is too well seene in this present subject; The sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this Kingdome (if any may be such where all are either Princes or Slaves) are to be the Twelve Tribes of the Jewes, and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Gentiles; what
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:114837:68"/>if ten of those twelve tribes be lost? they shall be found again; and be made Saints, that they may become sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; for else they should but be found out for a worse confusion; So then the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Tribes shall be built again and inhabited by naturall Israelites; espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> which shall be the most eminent city in the world,
<note place="margin">Pag. 26.</note> or that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was in the world; and at <hi>Jerusalem</hi> wil Christ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to shew himself; and then by and from the Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites shall glory descend to the Gentiles Thus runs the letter;
<note place="margin">Rom. 2. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </note> But the best Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter St. <hi>Paul</hi> tels us <hi>of a Jew outwardly, and a Jew within; of circumcision in
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:114837:68"/>the flesh, and circumcision of the heart;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 9.8.</note>
                  <hi>of circumcision in the spirit, and in the letter; of children of the flesh, and children of the promise,</hi> which distinction whosoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver shal have duly disgested, will easily find how wild a Paradoxe it is to tie those frequent and large promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of the Prophets made to <hi>Juda,</hi> and <hi>Israel, Sion,</hi> and <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> to a carnall li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terality of sense; and to make account of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment accordingly; which were never other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise then spiritually meant; and thereupon to affirm (as this Author doth) that even those ten Tribes of <hi>Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> which were 2340
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:114837:69"/>years ago, so dispersed (as the dust with the winde) that no man could since their dissipation say of any one of them, This was an Israelite; neither have they now any known being in the world, that they should be suddenly fetcht up again, out of the forlorn rubbidge of <hi>Paganisme,</hi> and <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme,</hi> wherein they are in many hundred generations irrecoverably long since, lost, and made the founders and citizens of a new and more glorious <hi>Jerusalem; credat Judaeus apella.</hi> It is true, that nothing is impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to an omnipotent pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; Had the Almighty said the words to their sense, no
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:114837:69"/>difficulty could hinder our assent. He can as easily raise Israelites out of <hi>Turks, Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, Indians,</hi> as out of their graves, but we know the sense of these propheticall promises and predictions, to be (as that Father said) <hi>in medulla,</hi> not, <hi>in superficie:</hi> In this just construction, there is no Jew but a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, and <hi>Jerusalem</hi> is built up, not in the soyle of old <hi>Jebus,</hi> but in the hearts of believers.</p>
               <p>Shortly, that we may clearly evince the morall impossibility at least of this mis-conceit of the reducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and flourishing estate of all the twelve Tribes whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converted to Christ,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:114837:70"/>their King, and the magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent re-edifying of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem,</hi> the event is in stead of a thousand arguments. It is but the next year 1650 or at furthest 56; which this Author (comparing <hi>Daniel</hi> with <hi>John</hi> according to his own calculation) hath pitcht for the performance of these great matters concerning the Jewish people; In which (saith he) the Israelites are to be delivered by being called to Christianity; both the Jewes who are two Tribes, and the Israelites, which are ten Tribes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And now where is the man that can tell us tydings but of a thrave of Jews new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converted, or of one
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:114837:70"/>stone laid in the new foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the new <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> So as the issue plainly tels our Millenarian Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren they have mistaken their aime; and sends them to seek for a truer and more verifiable sense.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>16</label> Well may it pass for a further Paradoxe, that the
<note n="8" place="margin">Paradox. The Saints in their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and immortall condition, medling with their earthly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.</note> that the dead Saints now raised to an immortall life, shall in those their spirituall bodies (so the Apostle cals them,) medle with the outward ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministration of the affairs of the Church; and have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall conversation with mortall men: controlling their actions, and ordering their processes, according to
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:114837:71"/>their Secular occasions; We finde that in the attendance of Christ's Resurrection, <hi>many of the dead Saints rose out of their graves,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 27.52, 53.</note>
                  <hi>and went into the holy City, and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto many:</hi> But that they ever offered to touch with any either Secular or Sacred business, wee never finde; these Ecclesiasticall Services, how holy soever, are too mean for so glorious Agents: And if they shall manage them, how and in what fashion shall they go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern? Shall they abate any thing of the priviledges of their glory, and immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Shall they be always Visible? Shall they be cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, or naked? since clothes
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:114837:71"/>are onely to hide shame, and to defend from the injuries of the aire; and there can be no place for shame in an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalized body, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst Saints, where there shall be no sin: And since their raised bodies are now impassible, and apt to the quick motions of spirituall substance, shall they confine themselves to these low places upon earth, and not lodge when they please in their former Paradise?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>17</label> As for those living Saints, who (if any at all) must be their subjects,
<note n="9" place="margin">Paradox. The living Saints, mortall, and yet sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less.</note> in what an impossible condition doth he make them? they must be mortall, and yet sin-lesse:
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:114837:72"/>What man or Angell can reconcile these two? They must still have originall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in them; that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied; but it shall be so yoaked, and restrained, that it shall get little or no ground of them: What a Paradoxe is this? If little, if any at all, surely they are sinners; and sin where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
<note place="margin">Revel 21.27.</note> what ever it be, defileth; <hi>now nothing that defileth or worketh abomination shall be there:</hi> None shall be in this Kingdome but such as shall be saved, such as are elected; but is it the priviledge of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection to exempt from sin? I had thought the fruit of Gods gracious election had been the remission, not the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:114837:72"/>freedome from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of sin: All here shal be Saints, no one (he saith) shall be an hypocrite; Oh happy Kingdome, where there is no taint of hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie!
<note place="margin">Pag. 27.</note> But shall men have hearts then? and are not the hearts of men deceitfull above all things? Though Satan be never so close chai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned up, yet the in-nate cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of that deceitfull heart, is able enough to breed store of hypocrisie: But what news is it that no person excōmunicate shall be there? what place can there be possibly imagined for an excommunication in a Kingdome (after a sort) heavenly; wherein there
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:114837:73"/>shall be no use of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
<note place="margin">Pag. 17. &amp; Pag. 29.</note> no use of any other Ordinances? wherein all shal immediately feed from God in Christ; wherein Christ will hold them all up in fulnesse of Grace.</p>
               <p>Yea, when there shall therefore be no use of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors, Doctors, Elders, Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, Preaching, censures in this holy and glorious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state, what spirituall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is that, which the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Saints shall exercise in the new <hi>Jerusalem?</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall the persons onely of the then-living Saints be freed from depravation by sin, but all their children in all the succeeding gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; none of them shall
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:114837:73"/>prove bad, none reprobate; all shall be called the seed of the blessed; what though they be begotten and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in sin? what though they propagate sin to the fruit of their loynes? yet their issue shall not prove sinners; As much to say, as there shall be fire, but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heat, nor smoke; There shall be a poysonous foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, but it shall yield no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholsome water. Neither can their be any danger of their languishing in grace, though they have neither word, nor sacraments; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall they have use of any improvment by the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>venly counsell, or examples those glorious and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:114837:74"/>Saints which they shall converse with, (which one would think should availe much to the continuation, and increase of their holines) but they shall have an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate fellowship
<note place="margin">Pag. 28.</note> with God;
<note place="margin">29.</note> and shall be edified immediately from God in Christ; But what? shall there be any use of their prayers? Are not those a part of Gods Ordinances? and the fellowship (he saith) which they shall have with God is not by Ordinances, but by God,
<note place="margin">Pag. 29.</note> and the Lamb; and what need they pray for that which they do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defeisibly enjoy? How e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; let it be scored up for none of the least paradoxes,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:114837:74"/>that GODS Ordinances should be use-lesse unto Gods people any where out of heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>18</label> That, under this Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of Christ,
<note n="10" place="margin">Paradox The fulness of all tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings of rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, honour, long life, under this Monarchie of Christ.</note> there shall be to the Saints for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeares all fulnesse of all temporall blessings, as peace, safety, riches, health, long life, and whatsoever else was enjoyed under any Monarchy, or can be had in the world or may make their lives comfortable savoureth too strong of a Jewish, or Mahumetane Paradise, as being extended in a fairer, and more modest expression, to those carnall pleasures, both of the bed, and the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:114837:75"/>board, which have been dreamed of by those sensual <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Talmudiges;</hi> It is true, that God hath been as exceeding rich in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, so no lesse large in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of all blessings to the children of the Kingdome, but those riches, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, are of another na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; purely spirituall, such as may be proper for the fruition of Saints: as for those outward favours, they are such, as the worst may have, and the best may want; such, as that a man may be happy without them, and he that enjoyes them most mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable; Such as wise <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> tels us,
<note place="margin">Eccles. 9.1.</note>
                  <hi>bewray neither the love nor hatred of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</hi>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:114837:75"/>And surely, if <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> did not find themselves enabled with strength, and health of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, with vigour of spirits, with outward wealth, and power, they would never offer, during the time of that Kingdome, to rise up against the Saints, in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen war. Shortly, we know <hi>the Kingdome of God doth not consist in meats,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro. 14.17.</note>
                  <hi>and drinkes, in houses and lands, in mines and mettals, in flocks and heards, but in righteousnesse and peace, and joy in the holy ghost.</hi> The enjoyment of good things for a moment, is scarce to be reckoned amongst bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings, since the grief of their
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:114837:76"/>cessation doth more then counterpoise the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their fruition; but here a long life shall make up the happinesse of the rich, honourable, frolick patriots of this new King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; for not one of them shall die early, what? not though it be to be transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from mortality to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall blessednesse: It is an advantage to be held off long from heaven? But who told this man, that no one should die under an hundred yeares old? It is true; he finds in the letter of <hi>Isaiah;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Isa. 65.20.</note>
                  <hi>There shall be no more thence an infant of days, nor an old man that hath not filled his days, for the child
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:114837:76"/>shall die an hundred yeares old;</hi> but he might have found also in the next words preceding;
<note place="margin">Verse 19.</note>
                  <hi>In Jerusalem the voice of weeping shall be no more heard, nor the voice of crying:</hi> well then; the husband, or wife, or child must dye at the last; and shall there be no teare shed for them? shall all the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects be exempted from all afflictions whatsoever; and yet be obnoxious to death, the utmost of all terribles? And how doth that promise extend to a freedome from all outward violences, and inward sicknesses, grief and trouble, which are the means and harbingers of dissoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet give way to
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:114837:77"/>that worst of evils, to which all these are but the gentle preparations? The truth then is; these are high Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legoricall expressiōs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it pleaseth the Spirit of God to set forth under bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily resemblances whether the prosperous and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table condition of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall Church, or the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py estate of the glorified children of the Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which, who so shall construe literally,
<note place="margin">Isa. 65.25.</note> shall in vain expect to see <hi>the wolfe and the lamb to feed together, and the lion to eat straw like the bullock.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>19</label> May it not well pass for a further Paradox,
<note n="11" place="margin">Paradox That so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thousand of glorious and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Saints raigning, the wicked, slaves and Tributaries should be able to raise war against them.</note> that whiles
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:114837:77"/>there are so many thousand Saints raigning upon earth, and indued with so much majesty and power to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the World, the slaves and Underling-Tributaries should be suffered to grow up under them, to such an head, as to defie their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and to bid battle to all those immortall Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers; any one whereof were able to quell a world of weake sinners? Who can thinke that the malice of these men should so far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed their wit, as that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by long and daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that these raised and glorious Saints, under whose iron scepter they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, are immortall, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:114837:78"/>impassible, they should yet hold it safe or possible to oppose them with any hope of success? And, if (to make the matter more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible) it shall be suggested (as it is by this Author) that they are drawne in by some deceitful trick of Satan; they could not but know the wisdom and knowledge of these glorious Saints to be such, as that they might much better then the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle say, <hi>We are not ignorant of his devices:</hi> So as if <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> shall hope either by wiles, or violence to prevaile against invulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, spirituall, and half-glorified powers, they shall approve themselves, more
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:114837:78"/>mad then malicious; And to make this Paradoxe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, how strange is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation, that this shall be taken for, the occasion of Christs comming the third time to his generall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment even the ruine of these assailants whom hee will come from heaven to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy; as if this witlesse and vain insurrection of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> could not be sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly &amp; powerfully crush<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by so over puissant op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posites; as if the blowing upon all the Legions of earth and hell could not scatter them in an instant.
<note place="margin">2 Kings 19 35.</note>
                  <hi>As if one of Gods mighty An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels who in one night destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an hundred four-score and
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:114837:79"/>five thousand Assyrians,</hi> could not as easily turn <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> into heapes or ashes; and yet the Son of God still keep his heaven?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>20</label> The third time then (he saith) Christ shall come down from heaven to earth,
<note n="12" place="margin">Paradox The day &amp; judgment to hold a thousand years.</note> for his finall judgement of the world; the day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of shall dawn immediately upon the expiration of the thousand years raign;
<note place="margin">Pag. 39.</note> but may (for ought he knowes) last another thousand years, as the former. The Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture indeed (he confesses) sets not down the time, how long it shall last, but long certainly it must last: And why so very long? and
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:114837:79"/>what do we talk of years when the Angel before this, <hi>swore that Time should be no more?</hi> what a bold weaknesse is this, to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure the infinite God by our selves? The necessity of the length of that time of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is evinced (hee saith) by the great work to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished in it; for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Gods Mercy, Justice, Truth, Power, &amp;c. is to be gloriously revealed before all mankind and devils; and the Truth of every Scripture cleared; and sinners silen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced or convinced; And se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, this is the time in which Christ Jesus is to triumph, and Lord it over all reasonable creatures and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:114837:80"/>wherein every knee shall bow to him.</p>
               <p>As if the Almighty should be limited to do his acts by leasure; as if he that made the world in six days, and could have made it in an instant, cannot as wel in that space of time judg it? Alas, what is time but a poore circumstance of finite mortality? not reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to the acts of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall? That Ancient of days may not have his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings confined to houres, days, moneths, yeares; and justly do wee say, that hee who is of himselfe one most pure and simple act, works in an instant; he can there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore gloriously reveale his
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:114837:80"/>Justice, Truth, Power, to men and Devils without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such leasurely respira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and if in an instant he can raise all flesh from their graves, why should we question whether he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not as soon judge them? As for the Trumph of the Lord Jesus over all his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as it is partly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished already, <hi>when hee ascended up on high, and led captivity captive;</hi> so shall it be fully perfited in the act of his last Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when his foes shal be made his foot-stool, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any such lingring forms of a protracted solemnity: For the performance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it is supposed by this
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:114837:81"/>Author; and his contests in opinion: that, whereas the Lord Jesus in his first com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming down from Heaven stayed not full 34 yeares upon earth: and in his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond comming down con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his visible presence amongst men, but til he had setled his government here in the world, and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to his heaven; now upon his third descent to Judgement, shall for some thousand years remain visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly upon earth, out of the locall heaven from whence he descended: A cōceit that would have sounded very strangely in the eares of our un-inlightned fore-fathers: Who were ever wont to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:114837:81"/>that this great busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the last judgment, being managed by the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wisedome and power of the Son of God, should be of a speedy dispatch; and that their returning Saviour should come to fetch up the bodies and souls of his elect to the instant fruition of their glory in Heaven, not to call them to a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand-yeares attendance on his visible presence here on earth; and if they found the Thrones set, and the Books opened, and all the processe out of Records, they were wont to construe these expressions as such, wherein the Spirit of God meant to condescend to
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:114837:82"/>our weaknesse, setting forth his own incomprehensible acts, by the forms of our humane judicatures which must necessarily both take up time, and require open evidences, and convictions; whereof there is no more use when we speak of an infinite God, then of Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Scribes, Registries.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>21</label> Well then, towards the end of the second thousand yeares the Judgement is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<note n="13" place="margin">Paradox A new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of a double hell, and the place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</note> the finall sentence pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed both of life and death, the elect are carried up to their blisse, the wicked sent to their place; both setled in their eternity; But here, I confesse, I stand
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:114837:82"/>amazed at the confident and peremptorie assertion of this Author, and other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers of his opinion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the place of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, and future hel. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, the departed souls of wicked, and unrepentant sinners, are not in custody onely, but in torture, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both separated eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the face of that God, <hi>in whose presence is the fulnesse of joy,</hi> and sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed upon immediately by the dreadfull executioners of divine vengeance; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not in that full ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisitenesse of torment, which awaits for them in that great Day; when their bodies, which were partners
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:114837:83"/>with them in their crimes, must also partake of their everlasting punishments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tophet</hi> we know is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared of old; and there is a peculiar place of uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveable horrour for the Devill and his Angels, and vassals; but where this place is, I have not so much war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant as to inquire, much less to determine: I must there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wonder whence these men receive their light; Certainly (that which was denied to the damned glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton in the Gospell) no man hath been sent thence to them, to informe them of these infernall regions of darknesse; and I am sure God hath no where revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:114837:83"/>this to them, in his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture: as not daring therefore, so much as to scan this point, much lesse to unlock so deep a secret, I lay my hand upon my mouth in silence, and dread; referring it to the glorious Angel that hath the keyes of the bottomlesse pit, and leaving these bold and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Dogmatists to their own concits.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>22</label> But though I may well fear I have over-wearied my Reader with the enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration of those ill-sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Paradoxes,
<note place="margin">Strange &amp; improbable consequents that follow upon this opinion, &amp; discourse.</note> which have not incidently faln from the pens, but have been studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously maintained by the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:114837:84"/>hands and tongues of the abettors of this Millenarie raigne; yet I must crave leave to put his patience to a further task, in viewing some of those incommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, mis-becomming, and improbable Consequents, which will necessarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low upon that opinion. I finde in a published Letter from D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Twisse</hi> of <hi>Oxford,</hi> to M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Mede</hi> of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> that this subject was pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately much agitated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt those two learned Divines; and that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor had furnished twelve compleat arguments against this Tenet; which if they could have come to my hands, might both have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114837:84"/>me light, and perhaps have saved my labour; In the want of them, I shall insist upon some of those harsh inferences, which offer themselves to my thoughts.</p>
               <p>Let the first be,
<note n="1" place="margin">
                     <hi>That in the Lords Prayer, we pray for this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie.</hi> Archer, p 10.</note> that in the Lords Prayer, we are taught to pray, <hi>Thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come;</hi> therefore we do therein pray for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishing of this Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall and personall raigne of Christ with his Saints on earth; when as, both such a Kingdome was never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged nor believed, by the Universall Church of Christ from that day till this hour; and it is clear, that it was Christ himself,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:114837:85"/>who taught the Disciples herein to pray to his Father for the accomplishing of his Fathers Kingdome, which is meerly spirituall not for his own personall, and visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as mediator.</p>
               <p>Secondly,
<note n="2" place="margin">
                     <hi>That Christ in his second com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to judge the earth should leave many wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live.</hi>
                  </note> how strange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth it handge together, that the Son of God in his second coming with much terrour for a generall judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all the ungodly in the world, shall yet leave ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wicked men alive to breed enemies to his Saints; to be slaves and tributaries to them in their new King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. For, as for those Saints that are raised up from the dead to an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall estate, they can have
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:114837:85"/>no use of such drudges; and for the Saints living; either they shall know the wicked courses of those surviving Vassals, or they shall not know them; If they know them not, they shall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective in their care, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versight, If they do know them, they shall be afflicted with the sight of their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednesse, according to the profession of the Psalmist, <hi>Mine eyes gush out rivers of waters because men keepe not thy Law:</hi> and if so, they are not in that happy estate freed from sorrow, which is strongly pretended; <hi>For in these times there shall be no sorrow or weeeping.</hi> Rev. 21.4.</p>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:114837:86"/>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>23</label> Thirdly, there had need to be a firm ground where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to build a belief of so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely a Truth,
<note n="3" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conseq. That Christ who hath all power should des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend from heaven to depute new Governors, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> that the Son of God, who, a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Ascensiō, could say, <hi>All power is given to mee both in heaven and in earth;</hi> and who, ever since, rules the Church by the <hi>Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riate</hi> of his spirit, as <hi>Tertul.</hi> expresses it, according to that order of Government, which he hath appointed; should now, the second time come personally down from heaven to depute new Governours in this his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, and having setled the administration in their hands should again take his leave of the earth: Further,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:114837:86"/>If those of the ungodly which will not stoop to the Scepter of Christ shall be the subjects of his destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<note place="margin">Pag. 13.</note> who can imagine that when he shall come in such heavenly glory, and maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, and in such astonishing terrour, there can be any person upon earth that will not readily crouch unto him, and offer to lick the dust under his feet. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, if Christ shall come down and after deputation of Governours ascend again into heaven, how can it be stood upon that this raigne of his, is personall for 1000 years upon earth? since personall presence and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation cannot stand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:114837:87"/>There may be a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall presence of the Prince in delegation of power to others, but a personal there there cannot be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>24</label> Fourthly, if this new Kingdome must consist of raised Saints,
<note n="4" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conseq. The strange composition of this ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi>
                  </note> and men-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; what a strange com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position shall here be of a government? what an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imaginable commixture of subjects? what a contempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature of heaven and earth? the bodies raised are spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, the living bodies flesh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; the raised Saints im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, the Saints living, mortall; and at an hundred yeares dying: what kind of commerce shall here be?
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:114837:87"/>how unequall, how unsui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table? how can it be other then a disparagement to creatures immortall, and glorious to be matcht with flesh and bloud? how can it be but too much honour for mortall, and earthly creatures ordinarily to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort with the blessed Deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of Paradise?</p>
               <p>Fiftly;
<note n="5" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conseq. All Saints, yet saith hardly to be found on earth.</hi>
                  </note> If all Saints that ever were before Christs second comming shall be raised; and the wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed; and the Saints then found living continued in the world, how shall that be verified which was spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by him who is the Truth; when the son of man commeth shall he find faith upon earth?</p>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:114837:88"/>
               <p>Sixtly,
<note n="6" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conseq. If the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles shall sway this Monarchie, how doth it agree to our Saviours words,</hi> It shall not be so with you.</note> If all Saints from the first man <hi>Adam</hi> to the last that expired before Christs comming, and all the believers then living shall be Rulers, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who shall obey? And if amongst the raised Saints, the Apostles shall (in their sense) sit upon twelve thrones, and as in a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall state on earth judge the twelve tribes of Israel, how is that verified, which our Saviour said to them,
<note place="margin">Pag. 8.</note>
                  <hi>It shall not be so with you.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>25</label> Seventhly,
<note n="7" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conseq. Adisadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the souls of the Saints in heaven to be fetcht down to the earth.</hi>
                  </note> what an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent dis-advantage should this be to the blessed souls of the Saints departed, to be fetcht down from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:114837:88"/>where they are in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect blisse, to spend a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand years upon earth, ere the consummation of their glory; to change the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Angels, for men; heaven for earth; To which main and choaking objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there is wont to be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a double solution. First, when those departed souls in the highest heaven,
<note place="margin">Pag. 22.</note> yet it becomes them, as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels do, to come down to serve the Saints, and with <hi>Lazarus</hi> his spirit, to return to their bodies again at the commandement of Christ. True; all creatures owe their due obedience to their Maker and Redeemer; and the more holy they are, the
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:114837:89"/>more ready still they are to pay this tribute of their humble obsequiousnesse to the will of their God, which is the supream law, without all pleas of their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences: But in this case, where shall we find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such command? where the least signification of the Divine pleasure? Surely should he bid any of them glide down to the dreadfull regions of hell it self, he would not stick at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; But assoon shall they finde the Almighties charge for the one, as for the other.</p>
               <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">Pag. 23.</note> they say, it is likely the soules of the dead Saints are not
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:114837:89"/>in the highest heaven, but in a middle place better then this world, but inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to the Imperial heaven: which is meant in the new Testament by Paradise: wherein certainly, Mr. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> hath shot strangely wide, both for the name and the place: Here can be no thought of the terrestiall paradise, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagined, which doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, was long since defaced by the deluge, that the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestiall paradise then, should either be called, or be a low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er place then the highest heaven, is no other then a grosse mesprisone I appeal to the blessed Apostle,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.2</note> who was rapt up thither, who
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:114837:90"/>tels us <hi>that the man he knew,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verse 4.</note>
                  <hi>was caught up to the third heaven;</hi> and straight, as describing paradise, for some more eminent part in that highest Heaven, he adds, <hi>that, he, the same man was caught into Paradise, and heard unspeakeable words;</hi> where, that we shall not need to imagine a double rapture of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as some of the Fathers, out of this place have done, it seems clear, that, contrary to this Authors assertion, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radise of the new Testament is the highest and most glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious place of the Empyreal heaven: which must cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be hence evinced, unlesse we will grant either
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:114837:90"/>two severall raptures of the Apostle, or an unnecessary and tautologicall repetition of one: for having first said, <hi>I know such a one caught into the third heaven;</hi> he sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes, <hi>And I knew such a man (whether in the body, or out of the body, I cannot tell, God knoweth) how that he was caught into Paradise and heard unspeakable words:</hi> so as his taking up into Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radise must needs be a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advance of that his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taticall rapture; the first rise whereof was no lower then the third heaven: Add to this, that when our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour said to the dying con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert on the Crosse, <hi>This day thou shalt be with me in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radise,</hi>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:114837:91"/>he could intend no lesse, then a place of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly glory; The Thief speaks of a Kingdome; our Saviour, of a Paradise; the Kingdome that was spoken of, was the Paradise which was promised.</p>
               <p>To this purpose is that,
<note place="margin">Greg. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servat. Iraen. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. l. 5. c. 5.</note> which our learned <hi>Gregory</hi> observes out of <hi>Irenaeus;</hi> who describes the Receit of just and perfect men, to be a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Paradise in the Eastern part of the third heaven; professing to receive that Tradition from the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Apostles: so as this Paradise (according to the best Interpreters) is <hi>coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li pars nobilior &amp; eminention,</hi>
                  <pb n="177" facs="tcp:114837:91"/>a more noble and eminent part of heaven; and if there may be any damage then, or dis-advantage in the change of a place of more excellence, for a meaner; in the change of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of blessed Angels for the society of mortall-men, surely it lies strōgly against this opinion, which fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Saints down from the fruition of an heavenly glory, to the government of the earth: But who told this Author that the Souls of the departed Saints are onely (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) as some ancients have expressed it? in some outer porch belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Court of heaven, and not in the inner rooms
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:114837:92"/>of those glorious mansious? In a place wherein they have full joy, and perfect happinesse, yet not where Christs body is: and that in this place they are kept till this Kingdom of Christ come?
<note place="margin">John 17.24</note> we are sure we hear our Saviour say, <hi>Father, I will that they also whom thou hast given me be with me, where I am, that they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the glory which thou hast given mee:</hi> and in his last Sacramentall Banquet with his Disciples, we hear him say; <hi>I will drink no more of this fruit of the Vine till I drink it new with you in my Fathers Kingdome;</hi> we are sure we hear the chosen Vessell who had viewed
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:114837:92"/>those heavenly palaces, say;
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1.</note>
                  <hi>We know that if our earthly house of this Tabernacle were dissolved, we have a building of God, an house not made with hands, eternall in the heavens;</hi> Lo, in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, not beneath them: and that immediately upon the dissolution of this earthly Tabernacle, not three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeares after it; and more then so long it must be, by their rule, ere the Apostles can be admitted into heaven; A thousand six hundred years are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy passed; and yet the thousand years raigne is not begun; a thousand yeares after that must passe, ere the end of the last judgement,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:114837:93"/>which shall enter them into the possession of their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. But a full confutation of any incident passages is no part of my intention: otherwise, I should willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall upon the discussion of those Scriptures, which are strained to the defence of that assertion; whereof yet there would be the lesse need, for that the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holds strōgly enough even upon their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessions, for if that Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise which they imagine to themselves be (though not the third heaven) yet a place of perfect joy and happiness certainly, the exchange of it, during those thousands of years, for so base and
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:114837:93"/>dungeon-like an habitation in this lower world, must needs be greatly disadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous.</p>
               <p>But if not in the highest heaven, where wil he think to place his Paradise? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, saith this Author, in the element of fire; A strange soyle, wherein to plant a blisse-full Paradise! But what if there be no element of fire? such Tenets surely the Schools afforded our younger days; some <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi> would tell him, that if there be an excesse of heat in those upper Regions un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the concave of the Moon, yet it is neither fire, nor elementall. But if upon some new Principles he shal
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:114837:94"/>make the substance of the starry heaven (which we had wont to call quintessen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall) to be the element of fire, I shall choose rather to wonder at that strange Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy, then to wrangle about it; wishing that it were no more unsafe to broach our own singular imaginations in these points of Divinity, then in these harmles speculations of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. However it be; whether either of them may be the receptacle of the departed souls of the faithfull, till Christs next comming, it is too much curiosity, to inquire, and no lesse presum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption to determine; sure we are, and it is agreed on
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:114837:94"/>all hands,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Wisd. of</hi> Sol. <hi>ch.</hi> 3.3.</note> that immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon their freeing from this clog of earth, they are in peace and unspeakable happinesse, whether in a locall or virtuall Heaven: neither need we doubt to say, that the full comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their glory, shall be in that great Day, when their old consorts their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies shall be joyned with them in the partnership of their consummate blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>26</label> Eightly;
<note n="8" place="margin">Conseq. Children of the Saints conceived and born in sin; yet still Saints.</note> how ill is it contrived to match such contrarieties in the same subject: The Children of the Saints, who are the free subjects of this Kingdome
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:114837:95"/>shall be begotten in sin, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and born in sin, and yet be true Saints, as if one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grosse actuall sins, from which they shal be restrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, were inconsistent with holinesse;
<note place="margin">Job 14.4.</note>
                  <hi>who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean,</hi> saith <hi>Job.</hi> If then they be pretended to be true Saints, why are they not cleared from all sin whatsoever; unlesse we will bring in the justly-exploded distinction of sins veniall and mortall, sins besides, not against the law, and shall free concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscence from the taint of sin; and so shall in the new Kingdome find out sinning Saints, or holy sinners.</p>
               <p>And how insufficiently is
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:114837:95"/>it pleaded, that there can be no hypocrites in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for that it being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministred by the raised Saints, they cannot possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly passe undiscerned by so piercing eyes; as if those sharp eyes of the raised Saints could penetrate the bosomes of men, and look into the heart, which the Maker of it hath lock't up for his own onely search, and intuition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>27</label> Ninthly;
<note n="9" place="margin">Conseq. No use of Ordinances, yet Prayers heard.</note> it suits not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-well that the subjects of this Kingdome shall not cōverse with God by Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and yet that they shall have a full and perfect answer from God, to all
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:114837:96"/>their prayers;
<note place="margin">Pag. 29.</note> since it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied that Prayer is none of the meanest Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Almighty.</p>
               <p>Tenthly;
<note n="10" place="margin">Conseq. Heaven dispeopled of all the ancient glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants for <hi>2000</hi> years.</note> upon this first Resurrection of all Saints at the next coming of Christ, how hard and harsh a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequent must it needs seem, that heaven or (as he will have it) Paradise, shall be for two thousand years at the least, dis-peopled of all their ancient and glorious inhabitants, the souls of Gods Saints, which have departed from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry instant of our Saviours return: all which are for that time housed again with their raised bodies upon
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:114837:96"/>earth; and there continued upon the employment of their Kingly administrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Eleventhly, how incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous doth it justly seeme that the soules of Gods Saints after their first disso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution should be in so vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, different and unequall condition, as that some of them should be ruling on earth, clothed with their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, whiles others which departed after Christs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming down, should (as new guests) be triumphing in Heaven?</p>
               <p>Twelvethly, how can it accord with that which the Apostle hath taught us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the last comming
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:114837:97"/>of Christ to judgement;
<note place="margin">1 Thess. 4.14.</note>
                  <hi>Them also which sleep in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, will the Lord bring with him;</hi> if the Saints shall be found all on the earth before him; as being raised by him at his second comming, to raigne here below till his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the finall judgement of the world? These and many more absurd inferēces may be brought, as necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily following upon the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of this first Resurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and raign of all Saints; if I did not feare to cloy my Reader, with distastfull su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>28</label> But, I may meet with some of our Millenari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Brethren,
<note place="margin">The opinion of the first Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of onely Martyrs confuted.</note> who disclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:114837:97"/>this more common opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the raising &amp; raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all the Saints, will choose rather to adhere to the cōceit of <hi>Alstedius</hi> &amp; his complices, who appropriate this priviledge of the first Resurrection, and thousand years-raign to Martyrs one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; as the first-fruits unto God, as purchased by a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular prerogative, from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men. For which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, they think fit to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret that, 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 4.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>propter quam.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>those that sleep in Jesus;</hi> by a strai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned cōstruction of the Prepo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sition: those that sleep for the sake of Jesus; wherein certain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly they are not wel advised; and will finde themselves strongly confuted, out of
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:114837:98"/>the very scope, and context of the place; It was the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles drift there, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort his <hi>Thessalonians,</hi> and to mitigate their extream sorrow for the death of those, which were dear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; whose decease he terms a sleep: can they thinke they grieved for the parting onely from their martyred friends? or did none but they sleep? the word is first generall, and absolute, ere it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained by any preposition; and, in the sequel, those which are asleep are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>distinguished to those that are alive and remain unto the comming of the Lord, so as all the faithfull which
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:114837:98"/>died before, are those that are asleep in Jesus; Neither can their interpretation find any relief from <hi>Rev. 14.13. Blessed are those dead which die in the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> that is, as they take it, <hi>for the Lord;</hi> The next words refell it; <hi>For they rest from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and their works follow them;</hi> Do none but Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs find rest from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in death? do none else find the happy reward of their works?</p>
               <p>And well may their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posers say;
<note place="margin">Revel. 4.4.</note>
                  <hi>We find not the four &amp; twenty Elders, which sate clothed with white ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and with crowns of Gold on their heads, to have bin Martyrs;</hi> and yet we hear
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:114837:99"/>them say,
<note place="margin">Revel. 5.10</note>
                  <hi>Thou hast made us unto our God, Kings and Priests, and we shall raign upon earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed, if there shall be any raign of the Saints one earth at all for those thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand years, <hi>Alstedius</hi> is sure too strait-laced to restraine this honour to Martyrs onely: How many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of Saints have their been that have been no less holy, and won no lesse ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to God in their stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then those which have bled for him? What shall we say to <hi>Abraham</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the faithfull, to him that wrestled with God and prevailed? to the rest of the holy Patriarks? to <hi>Moses</hi>
                  <pb n="193" facs="tcp:114837:99"/>the man of God that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versed so familiarly with the Almighty: So <hi>Elias</hi> that was rapt up to heaven, and to all the other holy Prophets? to the blessed Apostles, to the laborious Planters of the Evangelicall Churches amōgst Pagans? to those painfull Preachers of the Gospell which have willingly wasted themselves to give light unto others? shall we suppose that they shal lie stil in the dust, whiles one sudddain stroke of an Axe shall advance those o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the prevented resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and raign of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand years.</p>
               <p>Besides, if he will needs be literall, how much low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:114837:100"/>must the restriction yet fall? <hi>I saw</hi> (saith St. <hi>John) the souls of them that were beheaded for the witnesse of Jesus, and for the Word of God; and which had not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped the beast, nor his i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage neither had received his marke upon their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, or in their hands, and they lived and raigned with Christ</hi> 1000 <hi>years.</hi> For how many thousands have suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Martyrdome for good causes before the beast was bred, or his image or his marks heard of; or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Christ came in the flesh: such was the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Abel,</hi> the Proto-martyr of the world; such were the four score and five persons
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:114837:100"/>that wore a linnen Ephod, murthered by the command of <hi>Saul;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 22.18.</note> such was <hi>Zechariah</hi> the son of <hi>Jehoiada,</hi> slaine by the command of <hi>Joash.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chro. 14.21.</note> Such were those many thousands of Gods people that were massacred under the Tyranny of <hi>Antiochus;</hi> Neither doubt I to say that whosoever he be, that suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers for the testimonie of a good conscience, because he dares not violate any one of the morall laws of God, is as true a Martyr, as he that dies for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of any of the twelve Articles of his Creed.</p>
               <p>Besides,
<note place="margin">Socrat. hist. Eccles. 1.4. c. 27.</note> our Histories tel us of some very <hi>Arrians,</hi> and other Hereticks, that have
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:114837:101"/>yet given their lives up to Heathen Persecutors, for the name of Christ: Shall wee say that those men shall shall receive more priviledge from God then the most orthodox Confessors which kept their souls within their teeth: yet suffered grievous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and lived and died more holily? Shortly then, if we shall count this preventive Resurrection a speciall bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of God, it must needs be an injurious partiality in those, who shall make such a difference of Saints, as that the more holy shall in the retribution of the Just God, carry away the lesser reward, and the lesse holy shal for one act of an instan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:114837:101"/>suffering, be crowned with so great and long-last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glory; before them.</p>
               <p>Howsoever it be taken; Surely, that so much-urged text of 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 4. favoureth neither of them; for when the Apostle saith, <hi>Those that sleep, in, or, for Christ, shall rise first,</hi> hee speaks of one and the same Resurrection, not of two Resurrections, a thousand years asunder: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any clause in the whole Booke of God, that doth so much as seem to countenance (no not to intimate) this double Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in the sense pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or this raign of either Martyrs, or other Saints up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth.</p>
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:114837:102"/>
               <p>Which in a verity of such importance, is without all example, for all the holy doctrines of divine scripture do (as that Father said a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, contruth with each other; making good both themselves, and their fellowes; whereas this, not onely (if it could be true) stands alone; but, hath many sore brushes of contradiction both of text, and reason, to discard it from our belief.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>29</label> As for that evasion of <hi>Alstedius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Alstedius <hi>his evasion concerning this single expression of the Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenary raign answered.</hi>
                  </note> that the single expression of this supposed truth, is no more derogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the undoubted cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly of it, then that of the seventy Weeks of <hi>Daniel;</hi>
                  <pb n="199" facs="tcp:114837:102"/>which though but once mentioned in Scripture, yet is, and ever hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as a most sure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and undeniable ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; it cannot serve his turn in the case we have in hand; There is no lesse diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the comparison, then in the time; The one a thing past, and punctually fulfilled, the other, in very pretence, future: The one clearly layed forth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ambiguity in the relation (save onely that weeks of years, not of days are plainly signified) the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther full of doubtfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction; As well might he have instanced in many hundred passages of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:114837:103"/>especially in matter of historie, wherein the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghosts contents himself with single, and but light touches of report, and yet challenging no lesse belief then upon a thousand redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications; Far be it from him to entertain so uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable thoughts of us, as if we durst not trust God on his word, though but once spoken; we know him to be <hi>Amen;</hi> and that repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions adde nothing to plain Truths; but all the question is here, not of words, but of sense; not of what is said, but of what is meant; so as we have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to expect and require, that when a strange do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:114837:103"/>is raised out of the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of a doubtful text, it should be shewed to be seconded by the accordant testimony of other Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; which upon this matter lying now before us, can never be effected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>30</label> We are now falne upon the last part of our taske,
<note place="margin">No necessity from the text of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting this strange Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of the reign con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for.</note> which is to shew, that we are not by any necessity of this text, cast upon the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of these strange Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, of a double resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the body; and of such a raigne of the Saints upon earth, as is pretended: since the words may well bear o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more commodious and safe constructions, wherein
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:114837:104"/>our sober predecessors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented themselves to rest: for the terms here used, are (if we observe them) of much latitude. He saith, <hi>I saw the souls of them that were beheaded for the witness of Jesus, &amp;c. and they lived and raigned with Christ a thousand years,</hi> This is the first Resurrection. 1 We know the souls are some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times taken for the spirit that animates us; somtimes for the whole person; so the Proto-martyr tels us.
<note place="margin">Acts 7.14.</note>
                  <hi>Jacob brought down into E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt threescore &amp; fifteensouls.</hi> 2 That were beheaded; though in a Grammer-sense it signifies the time past, yet commonly in a Propheticall
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:114837:104"/>sense it signifies the future; it being the ordinary phrase of the Prophets, by reason of the infallible certainty of the events, to speak of things to come, as already past; the instances are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, and infinite. 3 The living raigning with Christ is, either in this life, or in heaven; present, or future, In grace, or in glory; In way of government, or of a blessed fruition. 4 The thousand years, either pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually determinate, or inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite. 5 The first Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, either of the soul, or body; either the Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the soul from sin, and a dead state of unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; or the Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:114837:105"/>of the body from the grave; and in the former construction, A Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either of a reformed Community, or of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar persons; All these then well put together, cannot but afford us our choice of orthodoxe, and probable interpretations, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny violence offered to the sense; Amongst the rest I shall pitch upon these two, as the most clear, and free from all just exception.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>31</label> The former, relating to the condition of Gods faithfull servants here on earth,
<note place="margin">The safe &amp; allowed con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>struction of the Text insisted on.</note> after those bloudy and generall persecutions: thus; I saw upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:114837:105"/>of Satan from that furious and universall vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, which by the hands of those cruell Emperours, he had exercised against the Church of Christ, such ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour put upon his faithfull and constant Confessors, during the time of Satans shutting up, as that the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was committed unto them of managing the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of Gods Church, and executing due censures up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the offenders; And I saw those godly persons, which in true Zeal of Gods glory either had suffered, or were ready to suffer and lay down their lives for the testimony of Jesus Christ, and those which consciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:114837:106"/>refrained from, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred the errours and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries of the times, those I saw to enjoy a comfortable life and spirituall raigne with Christ, in a sanctified and gracious estate here on earth; all the time of the thousand years of Satans restraint: But for the rest, which lay spiritually dead in their sins, and impious courses, they did not, either in that space, or afterwards; at all, attain to this life of grace, and to the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and fruition of God: Now this abandoning of the sinfull corruptions of the times, and attaining to the true knowledge, and love of the saving Truth of
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:114837:106"/>God, and a conscionable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience thereunto, is the first Resurrection. Blessed and holy is he that hath his part in this spirituall resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; for on such a one the second death, which is an eternall separation of the soul from the presence of God shall have no power, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The other, relating to the happy estate of the souls glorified in heaven, to this sense. I saw the souls of the blessed Martyrs after they were by a violent death, for bearing witnesse to the name of Christ, freed from the calamities of this wretched life, received up to glory; and raigning in
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:114837:107"/>heaven with their glorious Redeemer in everlasting happinesse; even during those thousands of yeares, wherein Satan was in his setters, and after that, to all eternity.</p>
               <p>If either of these con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions may fitly expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Text, and fully suit withal other Scriptures, to what purpose should we ransack the grave, and rake in the ashes of an odious <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> or an exploded <hi>Papias,</hi> for the long-since condemn'd conceits of old; and hitherto forgotten Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenarisme?</p>
               <p>I might easily, if it would requite the cost of time, lay before my Reader the just
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:114837:107"/>exception that may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken against divers of those other expositions, and the opinions thereon grounded, which I formerly specified, but I do willingly forbear them, as more worthy of silence and neglect. I had rather spend my time and breath in exhorting all good Christians to keepe close to their old Tenets; and to beware of all either new-devised, or re-divived errours of opinion: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this last age of ours is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorably fruitfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>32</label> Amongst the rest,
<note place="margin">An exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to stick fast to the old Principles.</note> let me beseech them to stick fast to their received principles in these four points which are
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:114837:108"/>incident to the matter that lies before us.
<note place="margin">And first not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve any Kingdom of Christ but spirituall and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly.</note> First, that they fix not their belief up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Kingdome of Christ our Saviour, but spirituall and heavenly: I am sure no other can be enforced upon them by the text; for it is not said, Christ shall raigne with them on earth, but they shal raign with Christ; rather intimating, that they should be fetch up to him, then that he should come down to them; and besides this raign is attributed to the souls not to the bodies of the martyred Saints; If it be urged that this raign of theirs is upon a Resurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from the dead, it is as easily return'd, that the
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:114837:108"/>resurrection intimated is no lesse spirituall then the soul which it concerns; <hi>Awake, thou that sleepest,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephes. 5.14.</note>
                  <hi>and stand up from the dead, and Christ shal give thee light,</hi> saith the Spirit of God: Lo, that sleep is death, and both that dead sleep and the awaking out of it is purely spirituall. Neither indeed is this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonall, and visibly Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall raigne of Christ o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then disagreable to the heavenly condition of the Son of God, in the fulnesse of his glorification; which certainly, if ever he would have exercised, it should have been when he was here like unto us, a man amongst men; that so he might have
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:114837:109"/>ruled over subjects sutable to himself; but now that his humane body is in a ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestiall and glorious estate, and his blessed deity shining forth in the full beams of resplendent Majesty, which mortall eyes are not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to behold, to bring him down from the highest hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to take the personall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of men, subject both to sin and death, (as <hi>Alstedius</hi> yields them) seems to be extreamly incongru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: And if we would ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine a visible and personall Monarchie, here must be all things correspondent thereunto, the place, the forme, the attendants, the officers, the lawes, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses,
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:114837:109"/>the rewards and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments in an outward bodily, &amp; little-other-then-secular way: all which how probably it may sound to Christian eares, I leave to the Judicious Reader to judge.</p>
               <p>Had our blessed Saviour, whiles he was here on earth, or his inspired Apostles af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, given us the least hint of this his future Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, we should humbly have prostrated our souls to the belief and expectation of it; but if men will be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing such Doctrines out of their private constructions of an aenigmaticall text, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of a more safe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived sense, we must crave
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:114837:110"/>pardon to with-hold our assent, and to leave them to their own imaginations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>33</label> Secondly, that they do not out of this conceit of a personall and visible King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Christ,
<note place="margin">Secondly, Not to think of any absolute freedome from sin, or affliction here below.</note> flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves into an opinion of an absolute freedome from ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sin, or bodily affliction here in this earthly life; since both these are, and ever will be the unavoidable companions of frail huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and the miserable symptomes of our fleshly nature.</p>
               <p>It is a true word of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaz</hi> the <hi>Temainte:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 15 14.</note>
                  <hi>What is man that he should be clean; and he that is born of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:114837:110"/>that he should be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous?</hi> Certainly, we must cease to be men, when we begin to be sinlesse; Sin though it be not of the es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of our nature, as some have erroneously thought, yet it is a proper, and inse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable adjunct thereof: which we cannot hope to be quit of, by the most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect regeneration; And as for affliction, he hath told us, that cannot deceive us,
<note place="margin">Job 16.33.</note> even Truth it selfe, <hi>In the world ye shall have tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and his blessed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles to the same purpose; <hi>That through many tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we must enter into the Kingdome of heaven;</hi> And,
<note place="margin">Act. 14.22.</note> if <hi>Alstedius</hi> shall hope to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:114837:111"/>the blow by shifting his foot, and referring the words to the present con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the persecuted Disciples; which yet should afterwards be interchanged with vicissitudes of calme, and peaceable times; he might wel have considered, that this life of ours is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily obnoxious to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other afflictions, beside violent persecutions; and might have paralleld that sentence with the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall observation of the great pattern of patience: <hi>Man that is born of a woman is of few dayes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 14.1.</note>
                  <hi>and full of trouble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither indeed can this conceit of theirs stand with
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:114837:111"/>that old, and never-contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted distinction of the Church Militant and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant; for if this Church of Christ upon earth shall after the next returne of him, be freed both from Satan (who is now chained up) and from all whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver afflictions, with what warfare shall we say it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised for the space of a whole 1000 years? what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary can it meet with for confliction? And, if <hi>Alste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> shall tell us, that in this meane while the living Saints (though not the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed) are still combated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in their brests with their rebelling corruptions; we send Mr. <hi>Archer</hi> to enter
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:114837:112"/>the lists with him; who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to make good upon him that those very Saints, whom our returning Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our shall find alive, are both in themselves, and in their children in all succeeding generations freed from all the power of sinne: so as though they have an origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall corruption still within them, yet it shal never break forth to the prejudice of their souls. So as by this rule, there should be no Church in the world till to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end of that thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand years but Triumphant: which surely a man had need of a strong faith to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
               <pb n="218" facs="tcp:114837:112"/>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>34</label> Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Thirdly, To expect no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther coming of Christ, but that one to his finall judgement.</note> that they do not entertain the thought, or expectation of any other future comming of their Saviour, but that one onely of his return to the finall judgement of the World: Surely, the blessed Apostle knew of no other, when he charged <hi>Timothy before God, and the Lord Jesus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.1.</note>
                  <hi>who shall judge the quick and dead at his appearance,</hi> to preach the word; when he prayed for his <hi>Thessalonians, that God would stablish their hearts unblamable in holinesse,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Thess. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.</note>
                  <hi>at the comming of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, with all his Saints:</hi> Lo, if there should be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined a third comming of Christ, we cannot say that
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:114837:113"/>he comes with all his Saints, since the greatest part of them, according to this Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, are already upon earth before him; and do rather stay for him below then come from above with him. And, indeed, wherefore should it be imagined, that the Lord Jesus should make this middle descent from heaven to earth? Great acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons must have answerable motives, what necessity, or use can they frame to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves of this wonderfull appearance; Is it to receive his Kingdome? He hath it already;
<note place="margin">Host. 2.8.</note>
                  <hi>Thou hast put all things in subjection under his feet,</hi> saith the Apostle: <hi>Already hath God highly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:114837:113"/>him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Philip. 2.9.</note>
                  <hi>and given him a name which is above all names, that at the name of Jesus, every knee should bow, of things in heaven, and things in the earth, &amp; things under the earth;</hi> Is it to settle the government of that his better reformed Church?
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.10.</note> It is done alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: <hi>He that descended, is the same also that ascended up far above all heavens,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">11.</note>
                  <hi>that he might fill all things; And he gave some to be Apostles some Prophets, some Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelists, and some Pastors and Teachers;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">12.</note> To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose? <hi>For the perfecting of the Saints, &amp;c. for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the body of Christ.</hi> And how long? <hi>Till we all
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:114837:114"/>come in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verse 13.</note>
                  <hi>unto a perfect man, unto the measure of the stature of the fulnes of Christ.</hi> Is it to subdue and destroy his enemies? Hath he not infinite power in his hand to effect that without a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily descent? when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed the first world of wicked men, did he descend from heaven to do it? So then we may with all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian assurance, rest upon the word of his holy Apostle <hi>Peter, That the heavens must receive him, untill the time of the restitution of all things;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 3.21.</note> which is, that of the generall Resurrection, as we may well see by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:114837:114"/>of St. <hi>Peter</hi> with St. <hi>Paul. Rom.</hi> 8.20, 21. termed by our Saviour, <hi>the day of our redemption:</hi> Till when, (which cannot be long) we have no ground to expect our Saviours return.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>35</label> Fourthly;
<note place="margin">Not to put the day of the last judgment far from us, nor yet punctually to determin the time of it.</note> that we do neither out of a credulous security put the day of the last judgement far off from us, nor out of a mis-groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded presumption passe our punctual predeterminations of it.</p>
               <p>In both which extreams these last times have been too fault-worthy: The time was when the Apostle was fain to beat off his <hi>Thessalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> from the expectation
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:114837:115"/>of the then-instant appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Christ to judgement; now, we have more need, after sixteen hundred years continuance to perswade our people of the approach of this great day: They did then believe that Christ was at the doore, now we are hardly induced to believe that he is upon the way to that dreadfull Judicature. Surely, This operation hath this Millenary doctrine had upon the hearts of men, that though they are thereupon apt to expect an appropin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quation of their Saviour for their happy advantage, yet they resolutely put off the thought of his comming to the generall judgement of
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:114837:115"/>the world, for many gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. A man hath a good estate in his Ferme for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most an hundred years; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, that is about to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase the inheritance in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version, after so long a term, is told it were better to spare that cost, since in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood the world would ere then be at end; he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers, Tush, no, the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand years are not yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, wherein the Saints shall raign upon earth before that day: In which yet this opinionist can be no other then grosly over-seen; For, is he a Saint, or is he none? If none, even the next com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Christ destroyes him, and marres his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase;
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:114837:116"/>If a Saint, though he make no purchase now, he shall then (according to their doctrine) live in all ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of riches, and earthly contentment.</p>
               <p>But, what if that thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand years reign be to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished in heaven, not in earth, as some construe it? or, if on earth, what if it be already accomplished, as others; where is then the confidence of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay? Certainly, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing this unhappily-rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed suggestion, nothing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, why we should not make full account that the world is near to it's last pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod; and that our Lord Jesus is at hand for his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:114837:116"/>judgement. For if in the time of the blessed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, it was justly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to be the last houre, needs must it now be draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards the last minute: Neither have we any reason to say with the evill servant in the Gospel, <hi>The Lord defers his coming.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may be a question whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be more out of bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to maintain that dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory assertion of the last judgement, which hath pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the pens of <hi>Alphonsus, Conradus, Cotterius,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or the confident and punctuall assignation of the time of those universall Ses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, determined by <hi>Alste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius, Archer,</hi> and others of
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:114837:117"/>that way: who can but be startled at those lines of Mr. <hi>Archer?</hi> Now (saith he) having found out when Christs Kingdome,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Personall raigne. p.</hi> 50</note> or the thousand years shall begin, it is easie to guesse when the time of the last and generall judgement, and the worlds end shall be. Thus he. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the evidence is much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of both: For when shall that 1000 years reign begin? About the year of our Lord, 1700. saith he, following the steps of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stedius,</hi> who upon the same ground casts it upon the year. 1694. and both of them ground the Epochaes of their Calculation, upon that fore-mentioned place of
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:114837:117"/>
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.11.
<note place="margin">Dan. 12.11</note>
                  <hi>Frō the time that the daily sacrifice shal be taken away and the abomination that maketh desolate set up, there shall be a thousand two hundred and ninety dayes. Blessed is he that waiteth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verse 12.</note>
                  <hi>and commeth to the thousand three hundred and five and thirty dayes:</hi> Where the days (as I formerly intimated) are taken to stand for yeares; and withall it is supposed that the 1335 years are in order of time to take their originall after the expiration of the 1290 years; and both of them to take their rise from the termination of the seventy Weeks; <hi>viz. anno</hi> C'. 69. All which put together make up the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:114837:118"/>of 2694, which is the utmost period of the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeares raigne of the Saints; from which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we deduce the said thousand, there must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main 1694. The <hi>initium Regni</hi> of the Lord of glory here upon earth; But if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the taking away of the daily sacrifice and the deso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latory abomination be not understood in that place of the act and armie of the <hi>Romans:</hi> Or the days there mentioned be not intended to stand for so many years: as being onely to signifie the short time of <hi>Antiochus</hi> his cruell persecution; Or lastly, if those two severall numbers were not meant
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:114837:118"/>to be successive one to the other, in the whole eompu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of them (which lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Calviu</hi> plainly censures for a vain and groundlesse conceit) all this aime and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is lost, and we are yet to seek where to pitch the account either for begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or termination.</p>
               <p>Shortly, what heed is to be given to this reckoning appears in that first parcell of it which concerns the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall conversion of the Jews: which Mr. <hi>Archer</hi> with the like confidence places upon 1650, now entred upon by our Almanacks, or at the furthest 1656. Wherein we see his Prognostication fails him; and his prediction is
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:114837:119"/>sufficiently checked by the event; No otherwise then Mr. <hi>Brightmans;</hi> by whose accompt, the Turkish Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny should have lasted but seven yeares after he wrote his <hi>Revelation;</hi> where as now near forty yeares are since passed, and that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire holds up still in too much vigour, without any appearance of diminution.</p>
               <p>What should I need to shew how others both of our countrymen and forai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, who thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves wiser then their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, have been shamefully baffled in their fore-deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of the last day of the world, which themselves have been suffered to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live.
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:114837:119"/>It will well become modest Christians to rest in revealed Truths, and to leave the unlocking of the secret Cabinets of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, to the onely key of his Divine Wisedome, and Omniscience; as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring the words of our Saviour: <hi>Of that day and hour knoweth no man, no not the Angels of heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let it be our care to be ever in a perpetuall posture of readinesse for that awfull and glorious comming of our Lord, and Saviour, whensoever it shall be; and to see that our accompts be set right for that great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit; so shall we meet our returning Master with a
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:114837:120"/>comfortable and happy as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance, and hear from him that blessed <hi>Euge, Wel done, good and faithful Servant; Enter into thy Masters joy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:114837:120"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114837:121"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114837:121"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Pag.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">line</cell>
                     <cell role="label">For</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Read</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Joannes</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>James</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Joannes</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>James</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>To matter</cell>
                     <cell>To make the matter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>Usuall</cell>
                     <cell>usually</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Two</cell>
                     <cell>too</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>By</cell>
                     <cell>of</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>69</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mar.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>62</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>doubtlesse but</cell>
                     <cell>Doubtlesse it shall</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>140</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Talmudiges</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Talmudiques</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>142</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>It is</cell>
                     <cell>Is it</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>167</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>Where</cell>
                     <cell>When</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>183</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>March</cell>
                     <cell>make</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>192</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>one</cell>
                     <cell>on</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>192</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>For</cell>
                     <cell>to</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>173</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>Imperiall</cell>
                     <cell>Empyreall.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Page 203 line 9, read and reigning.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>